If the
If the
,​
,​
Academia Sinica's November Knowledge Feast Lectures began.
中央研究院11月份知識饗宴演講會開始。
Wang Hansheng, vice president, hosted for us.
王漢生,副院長,為我們主持。
Director Li Jie, Dear Distinguished Guests, Dear Friends
主任李潔院長各位貴賓各位朋友
That's because Vice President Chen
那因為陳副院長這個他
have my agent
有我代理
Dr. Mingzhe is the Agricultural Biotechnology Research Center of our hospital
是名者博士是本院農業生物科技研究中心
Special Forces researcher and director are the agricultural and biological center
特兵研究員跟主任就是農生中心
He graduated from the Biology Department of Tunghai University in 1976
他在1976年畢業於東海大學生物系
In 1978, he studied genetics at the University of Elva
1978年到埃爾瓦大學公讀遺傳學
After getting a Ph.D. in 1983
83年得到博士以後
Postdoctoral research at Harvard University
到哈佛大學做博士後研究
In 1988, he returned to the Biology Department of the University of Elva to teach
1988年回到埃爾瓦大學生物系任教
Later served as a professor of biology at the school
後來擔任過該校的生物系教授
and Director of the Center for Comparative Genomes
及比較基因體中心的主任
After 20 years at the University of Elva
在埃爾瓦大學工作20年之後
in January 2008
於2008年1月
Apply back to our hospital as the Agricultural Biotechnology Center
應聘回本院擔任農業生物科技中心
Special Forces Researcher and Director
特兵研究員跟主任
And served as the forward-looking translation of the hospital
並擔任本院前瞻轉譯
Chief host of the Agricultural Cooperative Program
農協計畫總主持人
Director Shi's expertise is in applied molecular biology
施主任的專長在應用分子生物
and comparative genomics methods
和比較基因體學的方法
To explore the function of genes in plants and vitamins
來探討植物和維生物基因的功能
and the mechanism of message transmission
和訊息傳導的機制
His current focus is on plant
他目前主要著重在植物的
Molecular Mechanism of Flooding Response
淹水反應的分子機制
There is also the impact of environmental changes on Taiwan's downturn
還有環境變遷對台灣倒座的影響
And the color and fragrance of Phalaenopsis orchid
以及蝴蝶蘭花色跟香味的
gene regulatory network
基因調控網路
He also integrates cross-school teams
他並且整合跨校的團隊
Construction of Taiwan Agricultural Genome Database
建構台灣農業基因體資料庫
According to my observation, after Director Shi came back in 2008
依我觀察從2008年施主任回來之後
He played great organization
他發揮了極大的組織
follow the power of mobilization
跟動員的力量
In fact, Taiwan's related research fields
事實上使得台灣相關研究領域
quite different
有相當大的不同
Form many cross-school teams
組成許多跨校的團隊
and lead many large projects
而且領導很多大型的計畫
Also on behalf of Congress to promote Taiwan
也代表國會推動台灣
with the EU in the field of agricultural biotechnology
跟歐盟在農業生技領域的
Science and Technology Exchange and Cooperation
科技交流跟合作
And it is also the agricultural policy of Academia Sinica in 102 years
並且也是102年中研院的農業政策
Planning committee with scientific and technological research proposals
以科技研究建議書的規劃委員
The topic he is going to talk about today is
他今天要談的題目是
Sustainable Development of Taiwan's Agriculture
台灣農業的永續發展
we welcome him with warm applause
我們熱烈掌聲歡迎他
Thank you, Vice President Wang, Dean Li
謝謝王副院長 李院長
Secretary-General Wu and distinguished guests
吳秘書長還有各位來賓
that's great to have the chance today
那很高興今天有機會
Let's exchange opinions with you
跟各位來交換一下意見
That is, I am actually a wedding paper creature.
就是其實我是做婚紙生物的
The agricultural policy towards Taiwan is 2008
對台灣的農業政策是2008年
I have a chance when I come back to Taiwan
回來台灣以後有機會
That's how we got to know Taiwan
就是開始認識我們台灣的
The situation of agricultural development
那個農業發展的情形
that has some personal thoughts
那有一些個人的想法
that's great to have the chance today
那很高興今天有機會
I can discuss with you
可以跟各位來一起討論
then i will put my speech on the wedding schedule
那我會把我的演講婚程
Three parts of the big column marriage
大列婚程三部分
the first is
第一個就是
Discuss issues related to Taiwan's current agricultural policy
討論有關台灣目前的農業政策的問題
Then in the middle I'll bring up
然後在中間我會提出來
means I go
就是說我去
Do you think there are any ways we can improve these agricultural policies
覺得這些農業政策我們有什麼方法可以改進
can solve these problems
可以解決這些問題
and then the last part
然後最後一部分
Can you hear me?
你們聽得到吧
I'll get to the last part
最後一部分我才會講到
In fact, the real problem we have to face
其實我們真正要面臨的問題
That is the impact of global warming on Taiwan's agriculture
那就是全球暖化對台灣農業
what impact will it have
會造成什麼影響
Then how do we solve it
然後我們要怎麼樣去解決它
That...
那...
a little louder
稍微大聲一點
that...
那個...
help me fix it
幫我弄一下
seems to be broken
好像是斷了
May I
可以嗎
ok
可以喔
we should be...
我們應該是...
ok sorry
好,對不起
ok then we can start
好,那我們就可以開始
The Academia Sinica regularly
那中央研究院會定期
That is to say, it is important to our country
就是說對我們國家重大的
technology or social issues
科技或者是社會問題
make suggestions
提出建言
That is usually the dean
那通常就是由院長
to form a committee
來組織一個委員會
Hiring experts inside and outside the hospital
聘請院內、院外的專家
Then do the so-called policy white paper
然後來做所謂的政策白皮書
In 102, Academia Sinica published a book called
那在102年中研院出了一本叫做
"Agricultural Policy Building Books with Science and Technology"
《農業政策 以科技建築書》
The book is really thin
那這一本書其實薄薄的
If you are interested
那各位如果有興趣的話
It can be exposed from the network of our Academia Sinica
可以從我們中央研究院的那個網路當露下來
But this book is thin
但是這本書雖然很薄
Among them, only our Taiwan is currently
它中間只出了我們台灣目前
Structural Problems in "Agriculture Facing"
《農業面臨》的結構性問題
There are six questions in total
總共有六大問題
But one of them refers to
但是其中一項指的就是說
Our old farmer's allowance has become a political bargaining chip in the election
我們老農津貼淪為選舉時的政治籌碼
As a result, the book was published
結果這本書一發表
The next day the newspaper published a lot of news
第二天報紙就出了好多的新聞
I won't talk about most of the content
大部分我內容就不講了
Most of the scholars of Academia Sinica are hiding in the laboratory
大部分就是中央研究院的學者都躲在實驗室裡面
I don't know the sufferings of the people
不知民間疾苦
This is a relatively mild criticism.
這個是比較算是溫和的批評
Zhang Huaguan, the magistrate of Chiayi County, is
嘉義縣的縣長張華冠是
Xi Xiaolong is big big today
喜孝龍今天是大大大
He has one last sentence not in it
他最後還有一句不在這裡面
i saw him on tv saying
我在電視上看到他說
peasants will riot
農民會起來暴動
So let me start with this question
所以我就這個問題來先
i watch tv in america
我在美國看電視節目
One of my favorites is called
最喜歡看的一個就是叫做
BioNumber
BioNumber
Just use trees to explain the problem
就是用樹木來解釋問題
So I'm going to start giving you guys
所以我現在就開始給各位
talk about some trees
講一些樹木上的問題
This old farmer is the first one to look forward to history today
第一個這個老農今天花望歷史
In the 84th year of the Republic of China
在民國84年
It's the so-called our government's economy took off at that time
是所謂我們的政府那個時候經濟起飛
Plus the WTO issue
加上WTO的問題
So there will be imported food
所以會有進口的糧食
So our government will
所以我們政府就為了
So it's kind of like rewarding our old farmers
所以要等於是算是獎勵我們的老年的農民
So he set up a so-called welfare allowance for elderly farmers
所以他就定了一個所謂老年農民福利津貼
But a law called the Battle Form
但是一個叫做戰形條例
The so-called combat regulations are temporary and transitional
所謂的戰形條例就是暫時過度性的
In the future there will be a more permanent legislation to take care of our old farmers
將來會有一個比較永久的立法來take care我們的老農
In the 1987 of the Republic of China
當初在民國87年的時候
It is said that it will be included in the so-called national pension system
就有言以要納入所謂國民年金制度
In July 1996, the legislation was actually passed
在民國96年7月其實已經立法通過
Once the legislation is passed, it will be implemented in January 1997
立法通過就在97年1月公佈實施
Then the implementation of this announcement is to bring the old farmer's pension into the right track of the national pension system
那這公佈實施是把老農年金納入正軌的國民年金制度
But in July 1997
但是在民國97年7月
Our Legislative Yuan Passed Old Farmer's Pension to Restore the Old System
我們的立法院通過老農年金恢復就制
through the National Pension
以國民年金透過
So it's back to the Battle Form Regulations
所以就是又回到的戰形條例
This battle is up to now
這一戰行就是到現在
Before July 103
在103年7月以前
I'll tell you what happens after July
我等一下會講7月以後發生什麼事
Before 7 months old farmers today's application qualifications
7月以前 老農今天的申請資格
Yes, as long as you have been insured for agricultural insurance for 6 months
是你只要投保農保滿6個月
If you are over 65 years old, you can receive it for life
65歲以上 你就可以終身領
At the beginning of today, the old farmer paid 3,000 yuan a month
老農今天一開始的時候是1個月3千塊
The Democratic Progressive Party increased the price to 5,000 yuan, and the KMT increased the price to 7,000 yuan a month
民進黨加碼到5千塊 國民黨加碼到7千塊一個月
So when you are 64 and a half years old, you buy rural insurance
所以你64歲半的時候 你買農保
From the age of 65, you will receive 7,000 yuan a month for life
65歲開始 你就每個月領7千塊領到終身
Later, after Chen Baoji became the chairman of the Council of Agriculture
後來就是陳寶基當了農委會的主委以後
He tried to improve the old farmer's pension
他就想辦法要改善這個老農年金
So he introduced a bill and it didn't pass
所以他就提出了一個法案 但是沒有通過
So then it became a thing
所以後來變成一個事不像了
He just passed a person named Laolong last year
他就現在去年通過了一個叫老龍
Amendment to Article 3 of the Provisional Regulations on Old Dragon Allowance
老龍津貼暫行條例第三條修正案
just one amendment
就一個修正案
That is to say, if you have received the old dragon's allowance before the practice, it will be the same as usual.
那就是說修法以前你如果已經領老龍津貼的一樣照例
You after July 103
你103年7月以後
You need 15 years of rural insurance
你農保年資要15年
So he extended six months to 15 years
所以他把六個月延長到15年
To be able to spend the thousand-amount Laolong subsidy of 7,000 yuan
才能夠花千額的老龍津貼7000元
Then you feed six months for 15 years
然後你把六個月餵滿15年
half price
先領半額
Wait until the seniority reaches 15 years before spending the thousand amount
等到年資達到15年才花完千額
So this solves half of the problem
所以這個解決的問題一半
Because these have been received
因為這些已經領的
You can see how big our country's burden is
你可以看看我們國家的負擔有多大
This is me from our Republic of China
這是我從我們的中華民國的
Annual budget book Council of Agriculture's budget
年度預算書 農委會的預算
you can go
你可以到
to that Taipei network
到那個台北網路
every year for the past ten years
每年都在 過去十年都在
you put it in
你把其中
This is the Council of Agriculture
這是農委會
you don't count it the one
你不要算它的那個
reserve fund
預備金
this is its total budget
這是它的總預算
almost every year
每一年就差不多在
100 billion up and down
一千億上下
look at everyone
各位看看
How much does the old farmer's annuity cost each year
老農年金每一年花多少錢
50 billion or so
五百億上下
So the COA's budget
所以農委會的預算
at least half
至少一半
Spend directly on the old farmer's annuity
直接花在老農年金上面
But it's more than that
但是其實還不止這個
look at everyone
各位看看
there is an item
裡面有一項
COAG Development Lecture Subsidy
叫做農委發展講補助位
This talk about subsidy is not about
這個講補助位不是講
is a subsidy
是補助
List of agricultural losses in Taiwan
舉完台灣農業損失
then any
然後任何
Special for any township need
任何鄉鎮需要的特殊的
What's up with the poker bit
撲駁位有什麼什麼
it's all in there
全部都在裡面
look at everyone
各位看看
From 16 billion to 39.2 billion
從一百六十億到三百九十二億
So the subsidy from the Council of Agriculture
所以農委會的補助
about 80 percent a year
一年大概有百分之八十
used for subsidies
用在補助上面
If you only have 20 billion
你如果只有200億
No matter how good your agricultural policy is
你的農業政策再好
you can never do things
你永遠做不了事情
If it's just a matter of the old farmer's pension
如果說只是這個老農年金的問題
Then maybe if we change the old farmer's pension regulations
那也許我們如果改這個老農年金的條例
that can be solved
那就可以解決了
look at
你看看
we have other questions
我們還有其他的問題
the first is
第一個就是
Our Agricultural Pruning Questions
我們的農業修根問題
You probably often see it in the newspapers
各位大概常常在報紙上看到
But in fact, the original benefit was not only root cultivation
但其實當初的本益不是只有修根
that now becomes
那現在變成
Look at the area from our water to Taiwan's seeds now
你看看我們水到現在台灣種子的面積
About 250,000 hectares
大概是25萬公頃上下
Our paddy fields are about 220,000 hectares
我們稻田修根大概是22萬公頃
That is to say, about half and half
就是說差不多一半一半
Only half of the farmland is in use
只有一半的農地在用
half in pruning
一半在修根
We subsidize root trimming every year
我們每年補助修根
Are you in that old farmer's pension?
在不在那個老農年金裡面
another 10 billion
另外100億
It's in the Jiang subsidy
就是那個蔣補助裡面
There are other sub-items
還有其他的分項
A total of 10 billion in subsidy each year
總共每年再補助100億
Well, if you have these figures, these subsidies are really subsidizing farmers, that's fine.
那如果你這些數字 這些補助金真的是補助農民 那也還好
Everyone, take a look, this is the top five subsidies in the country published by the United Daily News
各位看看這是聯合報登的補助全國前五名的
The farmland they own, the money that has been subsidized by Xiu Geun for the past five years
他們擁有的農地 過去五年補助的秀根的錢
These people are not farmers, these people are investing in farmland
這些人不是農民 這些人是投資農地的
Therefore, many subsidies from our government have not actually reached the hands of farmers.
所以我們政府的很多補助其實沒有達到農民的手裡
but in the hands of some speculative class
而是在一些投機課的手裡
Well, if you look at the source of the original root repair policy
那如果你看看當初那個 看看當初修根政策的來源
Actually there are two parts
其實是有兩部分
In the 73rd year of the Republic of China, he actually wanted to teach farmers to cultivate their roots.
他在民國73年其實是要輔導農民修根 轉做
That transfer means
那個轉做的意思是說
accept government grants
讓接受政府的補助
fallow that year
那一年休耕
The right to use your farmland
你那個農地的使用權
to the Council of Agriculture
要交給農委會
integrated by COA
由農委會整合
distributed to other yeoman
分配給其他自耕農
Or go to the so-called small landlords
或者是去現在所謂的小地主
The concept of small landlords and big electricity farmers
小地主大電農的概念
This is how young people can be encouraged to grow chairs
就是這樣子可以鼓勵年輕人去種椅
In fact, this idea has existed since the Republic of China in 1973
其實從民國73年就有這個idea
But this law entered the Legislative Yuan
但是這個法條進了立法院
fallow still
休耕還在
transfer to see
轉作給看
so
所以
31 years later
31年以後
we still have only fallow
我們還是只有休耕
not converted
沒有轉作
Guys, don't think your fields are fallow
各位不要以為你農田休耕
put it there
放在那裡就
It will not affect
不會影響
nothing
沒有事
after fallow
農田休耕以後
if you don't take care of it
你如果不去照顧它
that place will
那個地方會
There will be pet pests and diseases, rodents
會產生寵害還有病害 鼠害
anything
什麼都來
So what you made is that farmland
所以你造成的就是那一塊農地
you do not need
你不用
So pruning for too long will destroy your field
所以修根太久 你那一塊地就毀了
And where are you pruning our excess power?
而且你修根我們多餘的牢利到哪裡去
cause social problems
會造成社會問題
Because if there is no place to use the strong power in the countryside
因為農村的牢利沒有地方用的話
Naturally, social problems will arise
自然就會產生社會問題
When we were discussing this white paper,
我們當初在討論這本白皮書的時候
Some committee members said that Taiwan is like kidney dialysis.
就有委員說台灣像洗腎的問題
It's because he listens to underground radio commercials in rural areas
就是因為農村他聽地下電台廣告
just took a lot of medicine
就是用了很多藥
Another Mark Six lottery may also be redundant in rural areas
另外一個六合彩也可能是農村牢利多餘
But this is actually Starly who didn’t do it carefully
但是這個其實都是沒有做仔細的Starly
so just listen
所以就只是聽聽吧
But it will cause rural police officers and rural social problems
但是會造成農村警官還有農村社會問題
absolutely no problem
就絕對沒有問題
if that's all
如果只是這樣 那也還好
created yet another law
又造成了另外一個法條
continuous evil
用的叫做惡法不斷
Because in 1989
因為民國89年
Our organization has made an amendment called the Agricultural Flower Regulations
我們組織做了一個叫做農花條例修正案
This is in my opinion the worst agricultural policy ever
這個是我個人覺得是有史以來最糟糕的農業政策
because it's the first
因為它第一個
It widens farmland acquisition restrictions
它換寬農地取得限制
In the past, it was not very profitable for you to buy and sell farmland.
以前就是你要農地買賣不太農利
You must be qualified as a farmer
你一定要具有農民的資格
You will pass it on to your descendants who will also be farmers
你要傳給你的子孫他也要是農民
Therefore, the inheritance of agricultural land is always under the hands of farmers
所以農地傳承永遠是在做農的手底下
And it changed
而且它這個一改
natural person can take over the farmland
還自然人接得承受農地
Natural persons are our personal inheritance of farmland
自然人就是我們個人承受農地就是
If a farmer wants to sell land, you can buy it
有農民要賣地你就可以去買了
Natural people have to bear
自然人就有承受
Second, it allows agribusiness corporations
第二個它准許農企業法人
Conditional inheritance of farmland
得有條件承過農地
The company you call yourself an agribusiness
公司你自己稱自己叫做農企業
then you can buy land
那你就可以去買地了
So it is equal to the free sale of agricultural land
所以等於是農地自由買賣
The worst thing is
最糟糕的是
Before Xiuhua, you have to buy and sell farmland
在修華以前你要買賣農地
You are not allowed to cut it into small pieces
你不准把它割成小小塊
You must have more than five hectares
你一定要五公頃以上
but this bill
但是這個法案
it revised it down from five hectares to 0.25 hectares
它把它下修從五公頃變成0.25公頃
So you can start mowing your farmland now
所以你現在可以開始把你的農地割了
cut a little
割了小小的
0.25 hectares is about 750 square meters
0.25公頃大概是750平
Section 18 of the Farm Digging Regulations Amendment
農挖條例修正案的第18條
I added this
有加了一個這個
in it this law
在它這個法條
Those who acquire farmland for 1.4 billion yuan are called farmers
十四億元取得農地者叫做農農
Actually no matter how old you are
其實不管你年紀多大
As long as you have this land before
只要你在以前有這個地
You don't care about the size of the farmland
你不管農地大小
you can change the farmhouse
你可就可以改農舍
The idea of ​​the farmhouse is you because you farm
農舍的idea就是你因為你種田
So you build on top of your farmland
所以你就蓋在你的農地上面
call definition
叫定義
but after january 89 you acquire farm land
但是在89年1月以後你取得農地者
They are called Xinnong
他們叫做新農
Need to obtain more than 0.25 hectares
需要取得大於0.25公頃以上
And it will take two years before the construction of agricultural works
而且遲滿兩年後方得興建農事
This looks like a good policy
這個看起來是很好的政策
That is to say, you can't be anywhere
就是說你不能隨便在
You can't build a house right after you sell the farmland
你賣了農地以後你就不能馬上蓋房
but you have countermeasures
但是你上有對策
We Taiwanese must have countermeasures
我們台灣人一定有對策
this is the worst
這個是最糟糕
It will be built after two years
遲滿兩年以後方得興建
Why
為什麼
because you're the one who buys and sells land
因為你要買賣土地的人
If he wants to sell it to others to build a house
他如果要賣讓人家去蓋房子
Then if people have to wait two years
那如果人家要等兩年
Of course he won't come to buy
他當然不會來買
so they figured out
所以他們就想辦法
Still Farmland Goushe Weird Phenomena
依然農地苟社怪象
It covers a small probably
它就蓋一個小小的大概
I think it's really like a kennel
我想真的是像狗舍
Everyone, if you go to Yilan, you will see a kennel
各位如果到宜蘭你看到就是狗舍
I think many people probably don't know why they cover this
我想很多人大概不知道為什麼要蓋這個
because it can sell land
因為它可以賣地
If you buy this person
如果買了這個人
people of this land
這塊地的人
because it already has
因為它已經有
This is called a ready-made farmhouse
這個叫做現成農舍
it can apply for extension
它就可以申請擴建
It can be expanded to the villa it wants
它就可以擴建到它要的別墅
so
所以說
The front looks as if it could be prevented
前面看起來好像是可以阻止
It is the misuse of farmland that has become this
就是農地的亂用變成這個
Then everyone, go through the Beiyi Highway
那各位再去經過北宜公路
you can see
你可以看到
It's called a kind of house, a kind of kennel
叫做種房子 種狗舍
one by one like this
一個一個一個 這樣子過去
these are all
這些都是就是
In preparation for the subdivision of farmland
為了準備把農地分割
Land for sale as a villa
賣成別墅的用地
The consequences of these agricultural policies
那這些農業政策造成的後果
Amendment to Agrochemical Regulations
就是農化條理修正案
It trades farmland subdivision restrictions
它換換農地分割限制
There are also qualifications for agricultural property construction
還有農財興建的資格
So good farmland is lost quickly
所以變成優良的農田快速流失
The production environment is also polluted
生產環境也受到污染
and the worst
還有一點最糟糕的
You probably don't know the definition of our peasant
各位大概不曉得我們的農民的定義
what is a farmer
什麼叫做農民
My hunch is that you must have farmed
我的直覺是你一定要種過田
farming, right?
從事農業對不對
But the census we do
但我們做的人口普查
Every five years we do something called the agricultural census
我們每五年會做一個叫做農業人口普查
if i tell you
我如果跟各位講
From the ninety-nine years of the Republic of China
從民國九十九年
From ninety-four to ninety-nine
從九十四年到九十九年
Our farm households increase by one percent
我們的農戶增加百分之一點
do you believe it
你各位相不相信
If you believe me there is a house on Mars that will sell you
你如果相信我火星上有房子可以賣你
that peaceful age of our farmers
那個我們農民的平靜年齡
Sixty-seven-year-old real Bunon's frontier
六十七歲真正勿農的邊境
Therefore, in the past 10 or 20 years, there has been absolutely no increase in farmers in Taiwan.
所以台灣過去10年 20年農民絕對沒有增加
Look at the census from that time, I think it's an underestimate
看看那個時候的普查 這個我想是低估了
40% of the so-called qualified farmers have never worked in the fields all their lives
有40%的所謂具有農民資格的一輩子沒有下過田
not engaged in farming
沒有從事農作
so this
所以這個
Therefore, if you obtain the qualification as a farmer
所以要如果取得農民資格
If both Yilan County and the Council of Agriculture want to restrict
如果現在宜蘭縣跟農委會都想要限制
The condition for obtaining the qualification as a farmer
這個取得農民資格的那個條件
But it means a lot of resistance
但是就意大很大的阻力
come down and listen to my
你們再下來聽聽我的那個
So now it's 2015
所以現在到了2015年
The organizing committee of Chen Baoji is very determined to do something
陳寶基組委他是非常有心想要做一些事
Including the government of Yilan County
包括宜蘭縣政府也
I don't know if they are cooperating
我不知道他們有沒有在配合
They are also considering this
他們同時就是在考慮到這個
Use administrative decrees instead of legislators to legislate
用行政法令而不是要到立委員去立法
Because of the administrative law, the words of the executive order
因為行政法 就行政命令的話
as long as
就可以只要
It won't be able to do it directly on the canvas
它不會就可以直接畫布就可以去做
So at the beginning of the year
所以本來在年初的時候
That is, the Council of Agriculture revises agricultural land and builds new farmhouses
就是農委會修正農業用地新建農舍
farmhouse approach
農舍辦法
The first one is to restrict farmers to build new
第一個它就是要限制農民才能新建
and buying and selling farmhouses
及買賣農舍
That is, you must be a farmer in your business
就是你買賣都要是農民
In case the farmhouse is improperly planted by intermediaries and consortiums
以防農舍被仲介還有財團做不當的草種
But when it comes to the Executive Yuan, it will be amended first.
可是到了行政院就先把它的修正
first cut in half
先砍掉一半
The Executive Yuan has decided that the builders of farmhouses are limited to farmers
它行政院還是敲定農舍的起造人限定為農民
this is no problem
這個是沒問題的
Because farming law is like this
因為農法本來就是這樣
But if the successor doesn't ask you, you will have to practice farming law
但是承受人不問你就要修農法
Because if you remember the farming method I talked about earlier,
因為各位如果記得我前面講的農法
It means that the recipient can be a natural person or an agricultural enterprise
是說承受人可以是自然人可以是農企業
So the Executive Yuan is
所以行政院這一點是
he theoretically stands still
他理論上站著住腳
He must go to the Legislative Yuan to amend the law
他一定要到立法院去修法
so this is no problem
所以這個倒沒有問題
So please ask this court to implement the first half first
所以說請這院就說先實施前半部
Later, the Nonghua Regulations stipulate that Chen Xiuren must be above the agricultural level
後面農華條例是規定陳秀仁要物農以上
And property farming more than one year
而物農一年以上
However, there are agricultural health insurance, health insurance and the third category no longer hold cash
但有農保 健保及第三類不再持現
if you only talk about this
你如果只講這個
Do not add the latter singular
不加上後面這個單數
I think it's a good policy
我想是個好政策
If you are in the Legislative Yuan, you can pass
你如果在立法院可以通過
Probably solved more than half of the problem
大概解決了一大半的問題
Why
為什麼
look at everyone
各位看看
What is the third category of insurance?
第三類的保險是什麼
Member of Farmers Association and Water Conservancy Association
農會及水利會的會員
He doesn't limit you to be a farmer
他沒有限制你是農民
to join these members
才可以參加這些會員
Also over 15 years old
還有年滿15歲以上
A civic approach to agricultural implementation
從事農業實施的公民方式
So this is a big loophole
所以這個就是個大漏洞
The second is that you have to attend the ceremony
第二個就是你要參加儀會
Become a fake class member
成為假類的會員
Or over the age of 15 engaged in a job for 1 month
或年滿15歲 從事1月工作
So you mean to say you join the farmers' meeting
所以你意思說 你參加農民會
You can become a farmer and buy agricultural insurance
就可以成為農民 就可以去買農保
This is to buy agricultural insurance and build a farmhouse
這個去買農保 去蓋農舍
So this is a big farmer
所以這個是個大農農
There is another way you can become a farmer
另外還有一個方法 你可以變成農民的
That is, you go to participate in the farmer distribution class of the Council of Agriculture
就是你去參加農委會的農民配信班
Two Issues You Are a Farmer
兩期 你就是農民
You can farmer loans
你就可以農民貸款
Then you can buy agricultural insurance
那你就可以去買農保
Then start to receive agricultural subsidies
然後開始領農農津貼
so we all thought
所以我們都以為
This was formulated by the Council of Agriculture
農委會這個制定的
This is actually just an amendment to an executive order.
這個其實只是行政命令的修改
should be no problem
應該沒有什麼問題
But everyone, look at the Apple Daily on October 4
但是各位看看10月4號的蘋果日報
there is
就是有
usually executive order
通常行政命令
Legislators have no power to review
立委員其實沒有權力審查
this
這個
The vice council organ politely sent it to the Legislative Yuan for future reference
副會機關客氣送到立法院所備查
But after this bill and this amendment are sent to the Legislative Yuan
但是這個法案這個修正案送到立法院以後
There are 18 legislators including Chen Chaomin from Miaoli
有十八個立法委員有苗栗的陳超民
These eighteen are all legislators of the Kuomintang
這十八個全部是國民黨的立委
Everyone will go, most of them will go
都是都會去的 大部分是都會去的
Accompanying them at the press conference is National Real Estate
陪他們開記者招待會是全國不動產
Chairman of the Council
上理事會長
They are against the Council of Agriculture
他們反對 他們要農委會
Sending this bill to the Legislative Yuan will change from reference to review
把這個法案送到立法院由備查變成審查
If you know
各位如果知道
Once you're in the legislature and you're under scrutiny, that's bad.
一旦你進了立法院要備審查 那就糟糕了
the spirit of your original legislation
你原先的立法的精神
Probably all of them will be changed. It's a mess.
大概都會被改了 亂七八糟
And among the 18 legislators
而且這十八個立法委員裡面
I promise you one or two may not be clear
我跟你保證有一兩個搞不好還分不清楚
What is the New Deal order? What is the legislation of the Legislative Yuan?
什麼叫新政命令 什麼叫做立法院的立法
I won't call names
我也就不點名了
But I want you to check the list
不過我想各位去看看名單
You'll know these legislators just sign
你就會知道這些立法人就隨便簽署
just come on
就說來來
Therefore, the Council of Agriculture is worried that the case will be brought back to the review room
所以農委會在擔心該案再立回審查室
I am also worried that in the face of the adversity of the law amendment
也擔心在面臨修法的逆境
So now our policy is stuck here
所以現在就是我們的政策就卡在這裡
These six items are what we set out in this white paper
這六條是我們在這本白皮書裡面
It is about the structural problems that Taiwan’s agriculture is currently facing
講的就是台灣目前農業面臨的結構性問題
The first is that I have already explained
第一條就是我已經解釋過了
It is the rapid production of environmental substances in the farmland
就是農田快速生產環境物來
I haven't talked about this yet
這個我還沒有講
The production environment affected by the second long-term root pruning policy
第二個長期修根政策影響的生產環境
Then the Nongjin post is what I just talked about.
然後農金貼這個是我剛剛講的
Then these are unreasonable agricultural regulations
然後這幾個這個就是不合理的農政法規
that this
那這個
Council of Agriculture, if you spend more than 80% of your budget on subsidies
農委會如果你把80%以上的預算用在補助上面
Of course you don't have money for anything else
你當然沒有錢做其他的事
So you can't blame the COA
所以你也不能全怪農委會
Because almost all of his money is in the Legislative Council and he has to do it
因為他的錢幾乎都發在立法會面臨他一定要做的
Mended must do
Mended 一定要做的事
So his budget is 100 billion since 80 billion is gone
所以他的預算一千億以來八百億就不見了
So he only has 20 billion a year to take care of our agriculture in Taiwan
所以他一年只有兩百億照顧我們全台灣的農業
so there is no way
所以那就沒有辦法
So these five are actually more or less related to our agricultural policy
所以這五個其實多多少少都跟我們的農業政策相關
what is the solution
那有什麼解決的辦法
There are short-term and long-term short-term solutions
那有短期有長期的短期的辦法
I just said something
我剛剛其實已經講到一些
In fact, as long as you really implement the existing laws and regulations
其實你只要確實執行現有的法律規章
Let me give you an example of a farmhouse
那我舉一個農舍的例子
certainly
當然
In the original development regulations, it was the regulations on rural development
在當初的發展條例就是農村在造的條例裡面
Paragraph 3 of Article 3 and Article 18 also provide
第三條第三款還有第十八條有規定
You are applying for farmhouse qualifications to be directly engaged in agricultural production
你申請農舍資格的是要直接從事農業生產
Then it is limited to farmers who do not have their own farmhouses
然後沒有自用農舍的農民為限
And other farmland must be used for agriculture
而且其他的農地一定要農業從事農業使用
Don't underestimate this executive
各位不要小看這個行政
You can implement this as long as you rely on administrative orders
這個只要靠行政命令你就可以執行
You execute well and I promise you the farmhouse problem is over.
你好好執行我保證你農舍問題就解決了
Why? You're the first to buy or sell
為什麼?第一個你買賣
To apply for agricultural qualifications, you must directly engage in agricultural production
申請農業資格你要直接從事農業生產
So you just win a review and don't let those fake farmers cover it
所以你就是贏個審查不要讓那些假農民去蓋
That's what the Yilan County Government is going to do.
那宜蘭縣政府就是要做這件事
The result is to pass this bill again
結果再要通過這個法案
In the past, there were a lot of this
以前就一大堆這個當初的這個就是
The brokerage of Huangwu went to protest in front of Xianzheng Five
黃屋仲介的就到憲政五前面去抗議
That is to say, it should not be strictly enforced
就是說不應該就是嚴格執行
What is the qualification of farmers
農民的資格的成何
But Yilan Constitutional Five is strictly enforced
但是宜蘭憲政五是有嚴格的執行
So he is going to build a farm now
所以他現在就去建農社的速度
It's less, that is to say, it's 20% slower
就是少了就是說慢了百分之二十
speak slowly
慢慢再講
So you just have to do your best
所以你只要好好執行你這個
You can probably do the first half of the policy
政策的前半步你大概就可以
Sale and purchase of farm cooperatives with closed farmland
收檔農地的農社的買賣
The second part you can make living there very uncomfortable
第二部分你可以讓住在那裡的很不舒服
Because of your other 750 ping you built a house
因為你其他的七百五十坪你蓋了房子
Other than that, you are here to do farming
以外其他的地你是要來做農業的
You can't tell me how many fruit trees I planted
你不能說我種幾棵果樹
or make some of that paper disaster
或者是做一些那個紙災
then you can
那你就可以
he regards agriculture as
他當成農業有
This is not legal anymore
這個都不合法了
so two or three months ago
所以兩三個月以前
The vice chairman of the Council of Agriculture is in Yilan
農委會的副主委在宜蘭
There was a farmhouse that was talked about
有一個農舍被人家舉話
He planted a few rows because of him
他因為他就種了幾排
he has a farmhouse
他有一個農舍
his house is qualified
他的房子是合格的
The size of the farmhouse does not exceed
農舍他面積沒有超過
One-tenth of that 750 ping
那個750坪的十分之一
but the lane next to him
但是他旁邊車道
Plus those street trees planted
再加上種的那些行道樹
usually illegal
通常是違法的
So if the Council of Agriculture or the county government
所以如果農委會或縣政府
Strictly enforce
嚴格執行
you go to practice every month
你每個月去開法
Remove his illegal things immediately
把他的違法的東西馬上拆掉
he must be living very uncomfortable
他一定住得很不舒服
His villa is only a villa
他別墅只有別墅
his way is gone
他的路也不見了
His potted plant is gone too
他的那個盆栽也不見了
His magnetic paper is gone
他的磁紙都不見了
you make him very uncomfortable
你這樣子就讓他很不舒服
Just you execute this
光是你執行這個
You can accept it as a farmhouse test
你就可以收當農舍的檢測
Then it depends on our county mayor
那就要看我們的縣市長
Is there an exception to this
有沒有這個破例
In fact, there should be a so-called long-term plan
其實應該要有一個所謂的長程的規劃
long-term planning first
長程的規劃第一個
you want to go back to that mother law
你要回去那個母法
You want to amend the Agricultural Development Regulations
你要修正農發條例
You need to draw paper, current agricultural construction methods
你要繪紙 現行農財 興建 辦法
because in every country in the world
因為在世界每一個國家
I think there is a so-called
我想都有一個所謂的
how to say strategic thinking
要怎麼講 戰略的思考
Let's say I want to feed my billion people
譬如說我要養活我十億的人民
How much good farmland should I have at least
我最少要有多少優良的農地
I can feed these people
我才能夠養活這些人
Then I divide the farmland
然後我就把這些農地分籍
I said I will never allow you to buy or sell these farmlands
我說這些農地我永遠不准你買賣
No, you are not allowed to develop it for industrial use
不是 不准你去開發成工業用
or other uses
或者是其他的用途
You have to have this kind of strategic thinking
你要有這種戰略思想
Then you must go back to our strictest one
那你一定要回到我們的最嚴實的那個
go inside the law
法條裡面去
Mainland China, don't watch it blossom randomly
中國大陸 你不要看它亂開花
it has some farmland you can never touch
它有一些農地 你永遠 touch不了
it is strategic farmland thinking
它是有戰略的農地思想
it knows it has to feed a billion people
它知道它要養活十幾億人
it must always have enough farmland
它永遠一定要有足夠的農地
So it doesn't mess with
所以它並沒有亂用
Although it is relatively marginal
雖然說就是比較邊緣的
that some farmland will be used
那有一些農地會被用
but it has a bottom line
但它有一個底線
We in Taiwan seem to have no bottom line
我們台灣目前似乎沒一個底線
If you arrive in Yilan, you will be very sad
你如果到了宜蘭 你就會很痛心
I just passed through Yilan for our self-speaking event last week
我上個禮拜 我們自講活動才經過宜蘭
You will find that half of Yilan's farmland has been removed
你就會發覺宜蘭農地已經去掉一半了
There is a villa in the middle of most of the farmland
大部分的農田中間都有一棟別墅
And then there's our rooting policy
還有就是我們的修根政策
In fact, the benefits of the root cultivation policy were good at the beginning.
那其實修根政策當初的利益不錯
you prune and turn
你修根轉做
This solves two problems at the same time
這個可以同時解決兩個問題
Our rural labor is not enough
我們農村的勞力不夠
If the government has enough
你如果政府有足夠的地
You take that subsidy for root pruning money
你把那些補助修根的錢
half for farmers half for farmers
一半給農民 一半給農民
Give these young people who want to go to the countryside let him come to Monong
給這些年輕人要下鄉的讓他來勿農的話
I think you can solve this rural labor problem
我想你可以解決這個農村勞力的問題
So if you make good use of the subsidy, it doesn't necessarily mean that it is completely wasted.
所以你補助款善用不見得就是說完全浪費掉
But if you just go and let him prune there
但是你如果只是去讓他修根在那裡
Then your money is really a complete waste
那你這個錢真的是完全浪費掉
And this old farmer should have done it long ago
還有這個老農今天這個其實早就應該
into our national pension system
並入我們的國民年金的制度去
You can't possibly have a provisional regulation that hasn't been changed in 31 years
你不可能一條暫行條例暫行的三十一年還沒有去改
I think this is something our government should think about
我想這個是我們的政府應該去好好思考的地方
The Basic Law of Agriculture is actually to combine all these
那這個農業基本法其實就是把所有這些
The bill I discussed turned it into a full statute
我討論過的議案把它給變成一個完整的法條
That's where our country's agriculture is headed
那就是我們國家的農業要往哪邊走
this i think
這個我想
Because I have probably mentioned that it is the employment opportunity for agricultural talents in our country
因為我大概已經提過就是我們國家農業人才就業的機會
Then the next step is actually the policy issue we are facing in Taiwan now.
那接下來其實才是我們台灣現在面前面那政策性的問題
You only need one or two exceptions to the head of government agency and exception to the mayor of the county
你只要一兩個有破例的政府的機關首長有破例的縣市長
Probably there will be many problems, and it should be possible to decide
大概問題會收當很多 應該可以決定
But what we are really facing is this problem
但是我們真正面臨的是這個問題
Our food independence in Taiwan is for food security
我們台灣的糧食自主力 為及糧食安全
You often hear about food security, but in fact it has a
那糧食安全各位常常聽 但其實它有一個
Let's say the UN's FAO in 1996
就說聯合國的FAO 在1996年
It has formulated a definition of what is called food security
它就有制定了一個叫什麼 糧食安全的定義
It simply means that when all people at all times have access to
它只是指說當所有人在所有時候 anytime都能夠獲得
and controlling sufficient quantities of high-quality food for an active and healthy life
及控制足夠數量的高質量的糧食來保證積極健康的生活
So now it's a matter of value and quantity
所以現在是值和量的問題
Enough and hopefully the entire population of the world
要夠 而且是希望是全球所有的人口
But now we are facing many challenges
但是這個 現在我們面臨很多的挑戰
The increase in population is also due to the need for quality
人口的增加 還有因為要品質
There is also an increase in agricultural production and a decrease in agricultural production.
還有量都要增加 農業生產也減少
The problem that the global environment becomes
全球環境變成的問題
That means we have to produce enough food
就是說我們要生產足夠的糧食
to feed the global population is a big challenge
來養活全球的人口是一大挑戰
Why, in fact, you look at food security
為什麼 那其實你看糧食安全
The most important thing is to look at the bones
最主要的你是要看骨類
Because bones are not just rice for eating
因為骨類它不只是米拿來吃的米
used as fodder
拿來做飼料
So bone is almost the vast majority of
所以骨類幾乎是絕大部分的
source of calorie
calorie的來源
So you have to see if the food supply is enough
所以你要看糧食供應量夠不夠
Just look at the global bone production
你就看全球骨類的產量
This blue one is from the past few decades
這一條藍色的是過去幾十年來
The one with global bone production
全球骨類生產的那個
increasing trend
增加的趨勢
That's actually a very
那其實這是一個非常
re-markable achievement
re-markable achievement
because you can see
因為你可以看
it's straight up
它是直線上升的
from the green revolution
從綠色革命
After the Green Revolution of 1960
1960年的綠色革命以後
Always
一直
keep going
一直去
that
那個
Straight up
直線上升
if that means
那如果就是說
We scientists are so good
我們科學家真的這麼好
can make this
可以讓這條
The food production line
這個糧食生產的線
keep this
一直維持這個
this
這個
is equivalent to a linear increase.
就等於是線性的增加的話
we will face
我們會面臨
In 2050 we will face
2050年我們就會面臨
food crisis
糧食危機
because this is
因為這是
demand
demand
this is your surprise
這是你的surprise
you can see until 2050
你可以看得到到2050年
This gap will be much
這個差距就會很多
that is
就是說
if we don't solve this problem
我們如果不解決這個問題
in 2050 there will be
2050年就有
food
糧食
worldwide
全球
food shortage problem
糧食不夠的問題
Once the problem of global food shortage
一旦全球糧食不夠的問題
there will be war
就會有戰爭
there will be a bend
就會有動彎
so this is a
所以這是一個
very important question
很重要的問題
What about us in Taiwan?
那我們台灣呢
food security, let's look at food independence
糧食安全,那我們看看糧食自主力
Everyone, if you look at the big countries in the world
各位如果看看世界的大國
Its agriculture must be ranked among the top in the world
它的農業一定是排在前世界的前幾名
Except for Japan
除了日本是例外
Everyone, take a look at Huaguo's food independence
各位看看華國的糧食自主力
300%
300%
so it is an agricultural exporting country
所以它是農業輸出國
US 120%
美國120%
Mainland China 70%
中國大陸70%
Taiwan 32%
台灣32%
So that means we need
所以意思就是說我們需要的
70% of calorie is imported
calorie 70%是靠進口來的
Then maybe you think you can buy it
那也許你覺得買就可以了
not so easy
沒有那麼容易
Everyone knows
各位知道
In addition to rice, these stocks in Taiwan
台灣這幾種股類除了稻米以外
we can be autonomous
我們可以自己自主
corn for feed
飼料用的玉米
barley, wheat
大麥、小麥
Rely almost entirely on imports
幾乎全部仰賴進口
Then you may think that money is enough to buy
那各位也許覺得有錢買就夠了
food is not that expensive
糧食不是那麼貴
In 205 there was a look a few years ago
在205年有看是幾年前
15 years ago there was a national
在15年前有一次全國
not the whole country
也不是全國
There are several large granaries in the world
全球有好幾個大糧倉
because of the drought
因為乾旱的關係
Mainland China India Russia
中國大陸 印度 俄羅斯
their country is in drought
他們全國乾旱
US pulls corn for reproductive alcohol
美國把玉米拉來做生殖酒精
So that year there were several places in the world
所以那一年有世界有好幾個地方
Its currency book is 4%
它的那個通貨本帳就是4%
4% is 50%
4%是50%
Because the corn sold in the United States
因為美國賣的玉米
closely related to everyone
跟每一個人息息相關
Most of the meat you eat is American
你吃的肉大部分都是美國
grew up eating american corn
吃美國玉米長大
pig sheep chicken
豬 羊 雞 都是
So that year Taiwan
所以那一年台灣
Almost put our so-called war food stockpile
幾乎把我們所謂的戰備存糧
Every year our Taiwan government
我們台灣每年政府
will buy some rice
會收購一些稻米
then save
然後存起來
after a few years
隔了幾年以後
Then remove the older rice
然後比較老的稻米拿掉
And then when we need
然後就是當我們有需要的時候
The government can provide emergency
政府可以拿出來救急
We almost put that
我們那一年幾乎就把那個
Our storage is all gone
我們的存養通通用掉了
Inflation in Taiwan did not exceed 10% in that year
台灣那一年通貨膨脹才沒有超過百分之十
Otherwise we will have a crisis that year
要不然我們就那一年就會有危機了
that so
那所以
This shows Taiwan's food insecurity
這個就顯示出台灣的糧食不安全性
That
那
Rice everyone look
水稻各位看看
We are 100% self-sufficient
我們百分之百可以自己自足
Then we need to import 6% because the WTO stipulates that we must import
那我們需要進口6%是因為WTO就規定我們一定要進口
but
但是
Now Taiwan is also starting to face problems
台灣現在倒作也開始面臨問題
It's just that I almost mentioned the farmland before.
就是我前面幾乎都提過了農地
We lost a lot of farmland
我們農地流失很多
rural manpower
農村的人力
and water resources
還有水資源
this is all
這個都是
the problem we are facing
面臨的問題
but in fact
但其實
more serious
還有更嚴重
Even God is looking for trouble
連老天爺也來找麻煩
everybody
各位
It's like global warming
好像就說全球暖化
I don't know if it will have a direct impact on Taiwan.
不知道對我們台灣到底有沒有直接的影響
Because summer doesn't seem to be hotter than before
因為夏天好像也不是說比以前熱到什麼程度
Although we complain sometimes it's hot
雖然我們有時候complain很熱
But climate and environmental changes caused by global warming
但是全球暖化所造成的氣候還有環境變遷
Some have particularly strong influence on Taiwan
有些對台灣的影響特別大
Average daytime temperature in Taiwan over the past 100 years
過去100年來台灣的白天的平均溫度
only increase a little
只有增加一點點
will not exceed the level of world increase
不會超過世界增加的水準
But our night temperature is the average temperature at night
但是我們的夜溫就是晚上的平均溫度
just increase it twice
就增加兩度
Don't underestimate these two times
各位不要小看這兩度
The global average pool is only 0.7 degrees
全球的平均池只有0.7度
Taiwan facility twice
台灣設施兩度
There is the International Rice Organization and they have scientists doing experiments
有國際水稻組織他們有科學家做實驗
If your temperature increases by one degree at night
如果你夜間的溫度增加一度的話
Your rice yield will be super white
你水稻的產量會超白的
Because usually the role of daytime light
因為通常白天行光的作用
night
晚上
colder weather
天氣比較冷
That means that the metabolism of plants will Slowdown
那個就是說植物的代謝會Slowdown
will be slower
會比較慢
So it consumes less energy
所以它消耗能量比較少
So it is equivalent to removing its energy at night
所以它晚上等於是除背它的能量
Then if your temperature is higher at night
那你如果晚上溫度比較高
Your metabolic rate will be higher
你的代謝率會比較高
So your output will be lower then
所以你到時候的產量就會比較低
this is the theory
這是理論
But that is to say, it should be considered as full REASM
但是就是說應該算是滿REASM
The climate change caused by global warming
那千球暖化所造成的那個氣候變遷
It's not just the high temperature I'm talking about
不只只有我所謂說的那個高溫
Sometimes Draught
有時候還會Draught
flooded
淹水
and extreme climate
還有極端性氣候
That's all scientific proof
那這個都是有科學證
That is to say, there are many reports
現在就是說有不少的報導
The so-called extreme climate is
就所謂的極端性氣候就是
You may feel that
各位也許可以感覺到就是
Although it is our average temperature
雖然就是說我們平均的那個溫度
The temperature remains almost the same during the day
白天溫度差不多維持一樣
but you can feel
但各位可以感
can it feel like
是不是可以感覺到就是好像
sometimes very cold days
有時候會特別冷的日子
a few more days
會多幾天
And sometimes it's very cold
然後有時候會特別冷
Especially hot days will pop up suddenly like this
特別熱的日子也會突然冒出來這樣
when it shouldn't be hot
在不應該很熱的時候
it will pop up
它會冒出來
So this is all documented
所以這個都有記錄
So although it is
所以雖然是
That is to say, it doesn't look particularly serious.
就是說看起來不是特別嚴重
But this is for agricultural aid countries
但是這個對農助國而言
This effect is particularly large
這個影響都特別大
the problem is
那問題就是
well if we admit
好 如果我們承認
That is to say, now there is global warming and climate change
就是說現在有全球暖化有氣候變幀
That's an upside-down for us in Taiwan
那對我們台灣的倒座
Does it actually affect
到底有沒有實際上的影響
that this
那這個
i don't have an answer right now
我現在沒有答案
But let's start by asking the question
但是我們開始來問這個問題
Does it directly affect
有沒有直接的影響
that climate change
那氣候變遷
that is to say especially that
就是說尤其那個
temperature change
溫度變化
resulting in two most important
造成有兩個最重要的
The most important influence on inversions is
對倒座最重要的影響是
Disease species and its accelerated evolution
病種還有它加速演化
I'll give you this example later
我等一下會給各位這個例子
Then it also affects
然後它也會影響到
Your output and real volume
你這個產量跟實量
This is an experiment conducted by academician Liu Shaocheng of our middle school
這位是我們中院的劉少成院士做的實驗
Then Barton 9 is Taiwan, as I mentioned earlier.
那Barton 9就是台灣就是我前面講過了
is our average daily temperature over the past few decades
就是我們過去幾十年來我們的平均日溫
it doesn't change much
它其實變化不多
But its temperature difference between the sun and the moon decreases and the temperature annoyance increases
但是它的日月的溫差減低 厭溫增加
This is Academician Liu Shaocheng's Publication
這是劉少成院士的Publication
If you have high temperature, what will be the impact on Taiwan's production
如果你有高溫對台灣的產量會有哪些影響
The first one, if you come in high temperature
第一個 你如果在高溫來的時候
It happens to be in the flowering period when the pattern is forming or the period when it is about to bear fruit
正好是它要在花紋形成開花的時期或是快要結果的時期
It will not be affected when the temperature is about 33 degrees
溫度大概33度它就不會受捷
As far as Pollination is concerned, the output will be low
就Pollination 產量就會低
As I said earlier, if you increase the temperature rejection, the production will decrease by 10%.
我前面講過你厭溫增加的話 產量會少百分之十
encouraged from
鼓勵從
That is, you take that, that is to say, you collect the gold
就是你把那個,就是說你收完金
and then, right there
然後再,就在那個
Endo Spen is when refilling is encouraged
Endo Spen 就是在鼓勵再充實的時候
If the temperature is very high, there will be fishy white
如果溫度很高了,那就會有腥霧白
I'll show you one of those later
我等一下會給各位看一個那個
A photo, then this kind of white rice with fishy mist is the empty egg
一個照片,那這種有腥霧白的米就是空包蛋
eat no nutrition
吃了沒有什麼營養
Then this is me from National Taiwan University
那這個是我從台大
At that time, the agronomy department was the play director, Lu Hushen
農藝系那個時候是戲主任那個魯虎神
Now is the era borrowed by the director of the Science and Technology Department of the Agricultural Committee
現在就是農委科技處處長借來的時代
Well, we in Taiwan actually have something to do with the planting of waterways.
那我們台灣其實對水道的那個種植有
Very good management, so every year the government announces
很好的那個management,所以每一年政府都會宣
Declare, review first, that is, you will
宣說,先審備,就是說你今年
How many farmers have to plant how much, how much
有多少農民要種多少,多少
the waterway of the work, and then he will estimate that is to say
工情的水道,然後他就會預估就是說
What is the total output of this strain you are planting now?
你現在種這種品系,總產量是應該多少
So at the beginning of every year he
所以他每年一開始的時候
He would say that I estimate that Taiwan will
他就會說我預估我們台灣今年
How much is rice production
水稻產量之位多少
Then one year later there are actual numbers
然後一年以後有實際的數目
Usually the Internet was established 20 or 30 years ago
通常網就是在二、三十年前
Our government is very powerful
我們政府非常厲害
The predictions are very accurate
那Prediction都非常準
That is, your total output
就是說你的總產量
The estimated output is about the same as your actual output
預估的產量跟你真的產量差不多
Then this is for our management
那這個對我們的Management
our economy
我們的經濟
It's very important whether you want to buy rice or not
說你要不要買米這很重要
But look at the past few years
但是在各位看看這幾年
This is the data Mr. Lu Wusen has
這是盧伍森老師有的data
In the past few years he has been on mission
在過去他使命了那幾年
almost ten percent
幾乎都百分之十
Does it sound like what I said earlier?
聽起來好像是不是就我前面講的
Because it means that the warming temperature of the previous autumn
因為就是說前秋暖化那個溫度
It seems that there will be a direct correlation
好像會有直接的correlation
Well of course it's not evidence
那當然這不是證據
but we're going to ask
但是我們要去問
Is this the reason?
這到底是不是這個原因
Why our output is higher than our estimate
我們產量為什麼會比我們預估的
so much less
要少那麼多
ten percent less
少了百分之十
that's a lot
那是非常多
that's what i said
那這個就是我說的
Encourage the enrichment period If your temperature is greater than 33 degrees
鼓勵充實期 你如果溫度大於33度
You will see this opaque
各位就會看到這種不透明的
this opaque this
這個不透明的這個
we call this
這個我們叫
negative new white
叫負新白
Then this empty egg has no nutritional value.
那這個空包蛋沒有什麼營養價值
because it encourages enrichment
因為它在鼓勵充實的時候
That nutrient has not been deposited
那個營養素沒有被deposit進去
So in Taiwan, you buy rice with that grade.
所以我們台灣你買米都有那個等級的
if you see
你如果看到
a lot of this
很多這種
that
那個
looks like
看起來是
pure white opaque
純白的不透明的
don't buy that
那個不要買
that is the cheapest
那個就是最便宜的
that so
那所以
that is
就是說
if you
如果你
pre-autumn warming
前秋暖化
will have the effect of these
會造成這些的影響
the most important
那最主要的
seriously ill
病重害
accelerated evolution
加速演化
so
所以
even if it is silent
就說這是也是如無聲
professor his age
教授他的時代
He just suggested
他就說建議
we are technically
我們在技術層面
what to develop
要發展哪一些
The first is to have
第一個就是要有
Breeding of softening two-fat rice
軟化兩脂米的育種
shadow technology
並崇害防治的陰影技術
water mixed and oxygen mixed
水混及氧混
Regulated Cultivation Techniques
調節的栽培技術
Surveillance and Outbreak System Recommendations
監測及疫情系統的建議
This is more traditional
這個是屬於比較傳統的
the field of agriculture
農業的那個範疇
So Chinese medicine hospital probably
所以中醫院大概
research in this area
在這個方面的研究
but this
但是這個
With some of our Chinese medicine hospital
跟我們中醫院的一些
teacher of plants
做植物的老師
there is some correlation
就有一些相關性
Because our hospital
因為我們中醫院
There are many teachers who make plants
有很多老師是做植物
The study of interaction with the environment
跟環境互動的那個研究
that so
那所以
so
所以
I am here
我在
Probably about five years ago
應該是在差不多五年前
we formed a team
我們就組了一個團隊
just want it
就是要
Actually the most
其實是最
to build
要來建
a platform
一個平台
that is
就是說
We consider that we are Taiwan
我們考慮到說我們台灣
how to quote this
要怎麼樣來引引這個
Global Warning affects us everywhere
Global Warning 對我們到處影響
Then its idea is that you want
那它的idea就是你要
Actually we're not the only ones thinking this way
其實不是只有我們在這樣想
In fact, the world told me
其實世界給我的來講
Now there needs to be a
現在需要有一個成為
Second Green Revolution
二次的綠色革命
and you
那你
The first green revolution was when you just
第一次的綠色革命是你只要
that is
就是說
with a lot of feedback
用大量的回料
Plenty of that sasom season
大量的那個沙崧季
Then you just have enough output
然後你只要足夠的產量
that's good
這樣就好了
But the new generation
但是新一代的
The Second Green Revolution
第二次的綠色革命
Because our problems are different
因為我們面對的問題是不一樣的
Because the environment you face is not like before
因為你面對的環境不是像以前是
Because you only need to overflow a seed before
因為你以前只要溢出一個種
because of your climate change
因為你的氣候的變化
not so suddenly
不會那麼突然
So our idea is to say
所以我們的idea是說
we want to build a platform
我們要建立一個平台
It is equal to having a Swar Team
等於是要有一個Swar Team
called the Rapid Strike Force
叫做快速打擊部隊
That cooperates with, for example, the person who makes the ring change
那配合譬如說做環變的人
They probably can predict
他們大概是可以predict
In other words, how will the environment change in the next few years?
就是說未來幾年環境會有什麼樣的變化
For example, Taiwan said that there will be drought in the future
那譬如說台灣說未來會有drought
there will be a drought
會有乾旱
Or say there will be too many fish
或者說說魚量會太多
Or in spring when it shouldn't be hot
或者說在春天不應該熱的時候
it will be too hot
它會太熱
then we hope we have that ability
那我們就希望我們有那個能力
It's from our tour kids
就是從我們的那個tour kids裡面
inside the toolbox
工具箱裡面
reserve one
趕快預出一種
Can cope with the next three or four years
可以應付未來三四年以後
The crops of the new environment
那個新的環境的農作物
That's because rice is the most important
那因為水稻最重要
So we use rice as our platform
所以我們就拿水稻來當我們的平台
just want to build a platform
就是想要來建立一個平台
equal to rapid strike force
等於快速打擊部隊
That is, we need to be able to quickly preseed
就是我們要能夠快速預種
you if we can predict the environment
你如果我們能夠預知環境
What kind of environment do we need our rice to face
我們要我們的水稻要面對什麼樣的環境
then we will pre-release this new platform
那我們就會預出這個新的平台
to grow in this environment
來生長在這種環境底下
This is our idea
這是我們的idea
So what we're looking for should probably be
所以我們找的大概應該就是
In our country, that is to say
算是我們國內就是說
Make plants interact with the environment
做植物跟環境互動
quite accomplished
就相當有成就的
mostly from
大部分的是來自
Academia Sinica
中央研究院
Agro-life Center Zhiwei Institute
農生中心 植威所
There is also a marriage office
還有婚生所
Then we also found the National Taiwan University Department of Agronomy
那我們也找了台大農藝系
and Central Agronomy Department
還有中心農藝系
And some teachers from the farm
還有農事所的幾位老師
We are mainly divided into three teams
我們主要分成三個team
The first is to resist disease
第一個就是要抗病害
The second is heat resistant
第二個是耐熱
The third is to raise questions and use
第三個是要養問利用
This is actually
這個其實都是
You want to develop permaculture
你要發展永續農業
will face this problem
會面對這個問題
So in total we have
所以我們總共有
seven sub-plans
七個子計畫
the first is
第一個就是
The first team and the second team
第一個團隊跟第二個團隊
It's me and Mr. Wang Qiangsheng
是我跟王強生老師
It is the Department of Agronomy of Central University
就是中心大學農藝系
And Teacher Lin Dajun
還有林大鈞老師
farm office
農事所的
Let's
我們來
to study Taiwan's waterways
來研究台灣水道
Osteobacterium albicans, pathogenic mechanism, and wedding papers
白葉骨冰菌 致病的機制 還有婚紙遇走
I will talk about the details of the comparison experiment later.
這個我等一下會講比較實驗的那個detail
Then the team used by Lu Husheng and Changyi is anti-heat
那這個魯虎生跟長醫用的團隊是抗熱
Then this, these four are the absorption of plant breeding
那這個 這四個是對植物養婚吸收
The wedding paper mechanism used
利用的婚紙機制
That's actually very important
那這個其實是非常重要
Because plants are the basic elements to maintain plant growth
因為植物 維持植物生長的基本要素
Including sunlight, water, air and minerals
包括陽光 水 空氣還有礦物質
Water and sunlight, of course, sunlight is free
那水跟陽光 陽光當然是不要錢的
but water water resources
但是水 水資源
So we hope that the waterway we pre-existed
所以我們希望我們預出來的那個水道
In the future, you may not need to use so many neutrons
將來可以不需要用到這麼多的這些neutron
especially mineral elements
尤其礦物質的元素
Like the egg spirit armor is the three most important we call marcoelement
像蛋靈甲是三個最重要的 我們叫marcoelement
That is, plants need a lot of nutrients to grow well
就是植物需要大量 才能長得好的營養素
some of that is tiny
那有一些是微量的
So several of our teachers have made eggs zero
所以我們的幾位老師有做蛋 零
There are also iron cores and copper ones
還有做鐵心 還有銅的
Then you may think
那這個各位也許覺得
what's so great about your elements
你這些元素有什麼了不起
Seems like zeros are everywhere
好像零到處都是
But in fact, zero is the most serious problem currently facing
但是其實零為是目前面臨最嚴重的問題
Because most of the zeros on Earth can't actually be absorbed by plants
因為地球上大部分的零其實都不能被植物吸收
Only a part of the limited amount can
只有一部分 limited amount可以
We call it bioavailability, which is what plants can use
我們叫做 bioavailability 就是植物可以用的
Then these zeros are only available in a few countries
那這些零就是只在幾個國家有
So you want the current zero return
那所以說你要現在的零回
That has already started means that it should be used up in a few decades
那個已經開始就是說在幾十年應該會用光
So the plants you're going to grow now are
那所以你現在要發展的植物就是
You need to be able to use fewer zeros
你要能夠用比較少的零
But still look good
但是還能夠是一樣長得好
Well, this is actually a big trick
那這個是其實是一大trick
easy to say
說起來很簡單
but not so easy
但不是那麼容易的
so
所以
Of course the egg is also very important
那蛋當然也是很重要
But because suddenly there are fine grains in it that can solidify the egg
但是因為突然中有細菁可以固蛋
So it should be relatively less deductible
所以應該是比較沒有那麼額減
But this and these three
但是這個還有這三個
That's what our comprehensive Nutrient team is doing
就是我們那個全面的Nutrient團隊有在做的
So we are the most plant-based nutrition team
所以我們最做植物營養的這個Team
Their most important thing is to improve the nutritional value of food
他們最重要的是要提高食品的營養價值
and improve crop quality
還有提高作物的質
And reduce the nutrition of sweet food
還有降低甜甜的食物營養
that this
那這個
if you can achieve this
如果你可以達到這個目的
you can help our environment
你就可以幫助我們的環境
call
呼籲
Because all the farmland now
因為現在所有的農地
Whether in Taiwan or around the world
不管是台灣還有全世界各地
are beginning to face the so-called prolongation problem
都開始面臨所謂的延化的問題
because you use too much nutrition
因為你用了太多的營養
Most of them are silent in the soil.
那大部分是沉寂在土壤裡面去
that of your soil
那你土壤的那個
If there are many of these Nutrient
這些Nutrient多的話
its continuation will
它的那個延續就會
relative increase
相對的增加
so you lose too many times
所以你失太多回
Your farmland will not be usable after a long time
你的農地久了也是不能用
So this can achieve several goals in one fell swoop
所以這個是可以一舉達到數個目的
The rest of the time I'll talk about my own experiments
剩下的時間我就講講我自己的實驗
Because Zhongyan always has to do experiments.
因為中研總是要做實驗了
I spoke a lot of formal questions today
我今天講了一大堆正式的問題
It's not good if you don't talk about some of your own research results.
不講一些自己研究的成果也不太好
so
所以
So right at the beginning of our project
所以就是在我們這個計畫開始
I was with Mr. Wang Qiangsheng from Chung Hsing University
我就和中興大學的王強生老師
we will team up
我們就team up
we decided to solve
我們就決定就是要解決
The so-called disease of Taiwan's waterways
這個所謂台灣的水道的病害的問題
There are three major diseases in waterways
水道有三大病害
The first one is called white leaf mushroom disease
第一個叫做白葉菇病
It was caused by a Seo Joon
那是由一個敘俊來造成的
The other one is called stealing fever
那另外一個叫做盜熱病
that was made by a
那是由一個
caused by a fungus
一個真菌來造成的
The other Wengu disease is also caused by fungi
那另外一個文姑病也是由真菌來造成的
Both bacterial blight and rice fever can be killed by good chemical pesticides
那白葉菇病菌跟道熱病都有很好的化學農藥可以殺掉的
Everyone, have you seen the Mystery Fever?
各位看過無謎熱沒有
Kun Bingbei once killed in a field and passed out
坤冰貝有一次在田裡面殺殺殺 昏倒了
He just wants to pre-spray
他就是要預噴
Because he just wants to kill pesticides and kill white leaf mushroom bacteria
因為他就是要殺農藥殺白葉菇病菌
So what I mean by this is that he can kill but is very poisonous
所以我講這個的意思就是他可以殺但是很毒
It's not good for the land, it's not good for people
對土地也不好 對人也不好
Usually this white leaf mushroom disease breaks out after typhoon
通常這個白葉菇病都爆發在颱風以後
Because after the typhoon, everyone will be injured
因為颱風過後 到處會受傷
Once the leaves are injured, it is easier for bacteria to enter
葉子一受傷 細菌就比較容易進去
So you often see that fever break out for no reason
所以你常常會看到那個道熱病就無緣無故就爆發起來
Usually there are some natural disasters
通常都是有一些自然災害
this disease
這個病
In fact, rice is being made all over the world
其實水稻全世界都在做
But we in Taiwan must do rice research by ourselves
但是我們台灣一定要自己做水稻的研究
there is a reason
有一個理由
Because there are two main species of rice cultivated
因為水稻的栽培種有兩個主要的種
North of the Yangtze River is called Japónica
長江以北的叫Japónica
It is the bee rai rice that you like to eat
就是各位喜歡吃的蜂賴米
The south of the Yangtze River is called Indica
長江以南叫做Indica
Your name is Zelami
各位叫做Zelami
Taiwan is the only southern country
台灣是唯一的南方國家
bee rai rice
種北方的蜂賴米
種 Japanese
種Japónica
Because the Japanese introduced it to the Bamboo Lake in Yangmingshan and began to plant it.
因為日本人引進到陽明山的竹子湖開始種
Slowly let it loop down to level ground
慢慢地讓它循環降到平地
After decades of breeding
經過幾十年的遇種
Our Taiwan is now the only one in the world
我們台灣就是現在全世界唯一
south country eat
南方國家吃
以Japanese
以Japónica
When our main rice is our door
當我們的主要的那個米食 我們的道門
There are pros and cons to this
那這個有好處也有壞處
Because at least I personally prefer to eat red rice
因為至少我個人比較喜歡吃紅萊米
And it's not very tasty in Leme
而在萊米不是很好吃
Because this is usually the pathogenic bacteria and its season family
因為這個通常那個致病菌跟它的季族
There is that special relationship we call a bend-to-bend relationship
有那個特殊的我們叫做彎圖彎的關係
That is to say, a certain physiological swelling
就是說某一種生理小腫
Strains that usually have some waterways
通常有一些水道的品系
It will fight against this physiological small swelling
它會抗這種生理小腫
it will have disease resistance genes
它會有抗病的基因
So there is that correspondence
所以有那種對應性
So it is very important for you to know what this physiological edema is
所以你知道這個是什麼生理小腫非常重要
Then there is a unit under the United Nations in the Philippines called
那菲律賓有個聯合國底下的叫做
International Water Course Research Center
國際水道研究中心
They specialize in Lemi our name is Indica
他們專門研究在萊米 我們叫Indica
Then they have 21 standard strains
那他們有21個標準的品系
each with a fungus resistant to white leaf mushroom
每一個帶一個抗白葉菇病的菌
Gene, that is to say, the waterway has that
基因 就是說水道有那個
Then if you go to Asian countries to collect his white patriotic disease bacteria
那你如果去亞洲各國去收集他的白愛國病的菌
You'll find 21 strains of white patriotism
你會發現有21種白愛國病的菌
Exactly almost 1 to 1
剛好幾乎是1 to 1
That is to say, if you carry this disease-resistant bacteria
就是說你如果帶這個抗病的菌
You can resist physiological swelling 1 to 1
你就可以抗生理小腫1 to 1
That's irresistible to others
那對其他的都不能抗
So this is an example
那所以這個是一個例子
You can see us talking about this
你可以看我們以這個來言
This one has this antibacterial
這個帶有這個抗病菌
Then you see he is not resistant to this white patriotic germ
那你看他對這個白愛國病菌他不抗
He only fights one or two
他只抗一個兩個
Then these two will be
那這兩個就會被
That is to say, he has similar healing bacteria
就是說他有類似的那個治病性的菌
So you have this disease-resistant bacteria
所以你有這個抗病的菌
you'll deal with this and this
你就會對付這個跟這個
but not resistant to other diseases
但對其他的都沒有抗病
So you must know the physiological small swelling
所以你一定要知道生理小腫
Only then will you be able to predict the disease-resistant water to
你才能夠預出抗病的水到
Then why does Taiwan have to do it by itself?
那為什麼台灣一定要自己做
Then I will give you the reason why Taiwan must do it by itself
那我現在就給你理由為什麼台灣一定要自己做
that's us
那就是我們
Just say when I come back
就說我回來以後
That is
那就是
on behalf of the farm
就替農事所
The existing Baiyugu bacteria in Taiwan
把台灣的那個現有的白玉谷病菌
Find the so-called wedding paper label
找到所謂的婚紙標的
help him
幫他
It's like helping him create that ID card.
等於是幫他建那個身分證
There are about five major species in Taiwan
台灣大概有五大種
That's probably distributed in
那大概分布在
distributed in these places
分布在這些地方
Then this is our 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 like this
那這個就是我們的1、2、3、4、5這樣子
You can watch
那各位可以看
should be
應該是
this top
這上面
And here's the frequency he distributed
然後這是他分布的那個頻率
That's really hard work
那這個其實蠻辛苦的工作
because
因為
Taiwan before almost 1990
台灣在差不多1990年以前
the collection of races
就說對生理小種的收集
very complete
非常完整
we collect every year
我們每年去收集
Our farming units are located all over the province
我們的農事單位在全省各地
collect back
收集回來
Then come back and put it in that freezer
然後回來把它放在那個冷凍庫裡面
Then you'll study its physiological properties in the future
然後你將來要研究它的生理特性
you can take it out
你就可以拿出來
But look at this picture
但是各位看看這個圖
Between 1990 and 2010
1990年到2010年之間
it collects infrequently
它收集的次數很少
Especially in the past ten years, almost completely broken
尤其這十年幾乎全斷
So we took out all the things hidden in the freezer by the farm
所以我們就把農事所藏在freezer裡面的總拿出來
Then compare it with what they collected back then
然後跟他們當年採集的一比
As a result, in fact, Taiwan used to
結果其實台灣過去
So there should be no new strains in the past 20 years
所以應該是20幾年來沒有新的品系
Just these four
就是還是這四種
One of them is called one and one be
其中有一個我們就是把它混成叫one and one be
so it's still
所以還是這
That means you haven't had a new one in the past 20 years
就是說你過去20年沒有新的
But if you do the independent trust test
但是你如果做獨信測試
Because we put these collected 20 years ago in the freezer
因為我們把這些20年前收集的放在冰箱裡面
frozen firm take it out
冷凍固定的把它拿出來
can activate it
可以把它活化
and ask how poisonous it is
然後問問它到底有多毒
Then put the newcomer
然後就把新來的
This is the same species, the same biological race, so let's ask how poisonous it is
這是同種,同一個生理小種,那我們問他有多毒
The answer is that Gang Xincai's toxicity is stronger than that of his relatives twenty years ago
答案就是剛心采的毒性比他二十年前的親戚毒性要比較強
That is to say, as time changes, his toxicity will increase
就是說隨著時間的變化,他的毒性會增強
So he is not there obediently, his toxicity is getting stronger and stronger
所以他不是乖乖的在那裡,他的毒性越變越強
That's what it means. If you want to predict your own in Taiwan, you must follow the evolution of the continuation.
那就是代表什麼,你台灣要預出自己的一定要跟著續盡的演化
You need to pre-produce new varieties that can resist these white frontal bone disease bacteria over time
你要預出新的品種,可以跟著時間來抗這些白額骨病菌
Then why can't we rely on others
那我們為什麼不能靠別人
Then we have the so-called high-throughput sequencing
那我們就因為現在有所謂的高通量定序
So you can easily fix the exhausted early hardware
所以你很容易定續盡的前期硬體
Then let's take Taiwan, both of which belong to Taiwan
那我們把台灣,這兩個都是台灣的
This is the most toxic, this is not so strong
這個是毒性最強,這個是不太強
Then if I draw a line here, it means his chromosome series here
那我如果這邊畫一條線就表示他的染色體這裡系列
a little different
有一點不一樣
You can see this one in Taiwan is very similar
你可以看台灣的這個非常像
no difference
沒有什麼差別
give you a test
給各位考個試
Hui Libing is closer to Taiwan
灰麗冰離我們台灣比較近
Then we also decided to continue
那我們也定了續
icy gray
灰麗冰的
Then Japanese and Korean bacteria
然後日本跟韓國的菌
Someone has already ordered
有人已經定續了
let's compare it
那我們把它拿來一比
You guys think it's relatively close
各位覺得是比較近的
Huili Bing's Baiyan Mushroom Bing's Mushroom
灰麗冰的白顏菇冰的菌
It is more similar to the bacteria in Taiwan
跟我們台灣的菌比較像
Or Japanese and Korean
還是日本韓國的
You guys are amazing
各位好厲害
Although Japan and South Korea are farther away than us
日本韓國雖然它離比我們比較遠
it is as it may be
它是因為它可能是
Because you have already said
因為各位其實已經各位講過
The rice season group followed it with bacteria
水稻季組跟它續菌
are co-evolved
是共同演化的
So it still has its characteristics
所以說它還是帶有它的特性
but there is a short book
但是有個淡書
This is from Taiwan
這個就是台灣的
this is korean
這是韓國的
this japanese
這日本的
It's icy gray
這灰麗冰的
If I have this kind of
如果是我這邊有這種
like crossed lines
好像交叉的線
just say
就表示說
it has major changes
它有很重大的變化
the location of that gene
它的那個基因的位置
In other words, genetically, it is actually a relatively large change.
就說在遺傳上它其實算是比較大的變化
Variability is relatively large
變異性比較大
So the more you have this cross
所以你有這種交叉的越多
means it is more different
就表示它越不一樣
so you look at japan
所以你看日本
Korea is different from us
韓國的跟我們不一樣的
mostly straight
大部分都是直線
But you see in the Philippines
但是菲律賓的你看
look
你看
but
但是
if you look carefully
你如果仔細一看
these crossed
這些交叉的
In fact, the most important gene
其實是最重要的基因
These genes are all genes that cause white face bone disease
這些基因都是白顏骨致病的基因
that is
就是說
Our Taiwan albino bone disease bacteria
我們台灣的白顏骨病菌
Although similar to Japan
雖然跟日本的像
but it has evolved a unique set of disease-causing genes
但它演化出一套獨特的致病的基因
so you have its unique disease-causing gene
所以你有它獨特的致病的基因
you need to be unique
你就要獨特的
Rice resistant to this disease-causing gene
抗這個致病基因的水稻
so
所以
Only Taiwan has this bacteria in the world
全世界只有台灣有這種菌
so you have to do it yourself
所以你只好自己做
what others do is useless
別人做的都沒有用
So why do we have to make our own rice
所以為什麼我們一定要自己做水稻
that's why
就是這個原因
Will do it for us, what others do is useless
會替我們做 人家做的沒有用
Everyone probably agrees that today is not my topic
各位大概對今天不是我的講題
Maybe next time Wang Mu will invite me again
也許下次王沐再邀我
Besides, genetically modified crops are very safe
再講基改作物很安全
But you all have this
但是各位對這個都有
there may be some problems
大概會有一些問題
but there is another way
但是有另外一種方法
You can actually pre-sum
你其實可以預總
And soon, it's called pre-marriage papers
而且很快的 叫做婚紙預總
Professor Wang Qiangsheng at the Agricultural Institute
王強生教授在農事所
image library
做了一個叫做圖片庫
That is to use Tainong No. 67
那就是用台農67號
Tai Nong No. 67 Everyone must know him
台農67號 各位一定要認識他
Because the basmati rice you eat
因為各位所吃的香米
What is the number of Geng, what is the number of Kaohsiung?
什麼台耿幾號 高雄幾號
All are from Tainong No. 67
全部都是台農67號來的
his descendants
他的後代
Because Tainong 67 has a large output
因為台農67號產量大
He resists many environmental adversities
他抗很多環境逆境
he looks good
他長得很好
Then he is also resistant to these bacteria
然後他也抗這些菌
some neutral resistance
有一些中抗
So he is the general manager of Taiwan
所以他是台灣預總的
the most important one
最重要的那個
So Professor Wang Qiangqiang used
所以王強強教授就用
We created a set called mutation library
就建制了一套叫做我們叫突變庫
That mutant library is yours
那突變庫就是你這個
inside his descendants
他的後代裡面
There will be many new features
會有很多新的特性出來
Then Mr. Wang started to plug
然後王老師就開始去塞
Then he stuffed some
那他塞了一些就是
Look at this ability to heal
看這個治病的能力
then he takes this
那他拿這個
I just told you about the XF89
我剛剛跟你講那個XF89
That's the most poisonous bacteria
那就是最毒的那個白額固病菌
Then he goes to try these and that mutant library
然後他去試這些那個突變庫
he finds out
他找出就是說
This is the earliest rice in Taiwan called Tainong No. 1
這個是台灣最早的叫做台農一號水稻
Then this is Tainong No. 67
那這個是台農六十七號
That's the size he's really sick
那這是他就病真的那個大小
Then you can see that Tainong-1 is almost immune to resistance
那你可以看到台農一號幾乎不抗
Tainong No. 1 is almost irresistible
台農一號幾乎不抗
Tainong No. 67 still has a considerable degree of resistance
台農六十七號還有相當程度的抗
But Teacher Wang found a few
但是王老師找到幾個
It is the descendant of Tainong No. 67
就是台農67號的後代
Then the following is the data in front of him
那下面這個就是他前面的那些數據
You can see this is Tainong 1
你可以看到這是台農1號
Natai Nong No. 67
那台農67號
And this is stuffed by Mr. Wang
還有這個是王老師塞出來
you can see most of his
你可以看到他大部分
This is how we measure his ability to heal
這是我們測量他治病能力的強弱
Then you can see Mr. Wang's rice
那你可以看到王老師的水稻
The new strain is very good
新的這個品系非常好
Then I can introduce by the way
那我可以順便介紹一下
You probably don't know us
各位大概不知道我們這些
the name of the crop field grown
那個農作物域種出來的命名
Everyone, if you hear Tainong
各位如果是聽到台農
Whether it's ripe bananas or anything
不管是香蕉歡熟什麼
just call tainong
只要叫台農
It's all from our farming area
都是我們的農事所域出來
Then if you hear Kaohsiung
那如果各位聽到高雄
What is the number in Kaohsiung
幾號高雄幾號
That's from the Kaohsiung Improvement Factory.
那是高雄改良廠出來了
Then each of our counties and cities has an improvement plant
那我們每一個縣市都有一個改良廠
But only those under the Council of Agriculture
但是只有農委會屬下的
have a flagship research unit
有一個旗艦的研究單位
Agricultural Laboratory
叫做農業試驗所
So everyone, as long as you hear Tainong
那所以各位只要聽到台農
Probably they came out of the domain
大概就是他們域出來
Their contribution to Taiwan's agriculture
他們對台農業貢獻
It's very big, everyone can do it, almost all vegetables and fruits have Tainong
非常大 各位可以 你幾乎所有蔬菜 水果都有台農
Everyone can, you should not be able to imagine
各位可以 你應該可以想像不到
The Yuquan fragrant pear you like to eat is called Tainong No. 71
那你們喜歡吃的玉拳香梨 叫做台農71號
Probably in the year after next, there will be Tainong No. 77 in the next few years
大概後年 再下幾年就有台農77號
Even more fragrant than Tainong No. 71, not very easy to grow
比台農71號還要香 不太好種
Because if it is fragrant, it is easy to attract sparrows
因為它香的話 就容易引來麻雀
So, once Mr. Wang finds this
所以 所以那一旦王老師找到了這個
This Tainong No. 67 that can resist the white ear bone disease bacteria in Taiwan
會抗台灣的白耳骨病菌的這個台農67號
That's because Tainong No. 67 is still not as delicious as Tainong No. 71
那因為台農67號 還是沒有台農71號的好吃
So it's now going to be called a backcross
所以它現在就要所謂回交
In the case of backcrossing, it probably means that you want to pass it back from generation to generation.
那回交的話 大概就是 你要一代一代的這樣傳回去
Then Teacher Wang started in 2014, so you are now in 2015
那王老師從2014年開始 那你現在2015年
That is to say, what you mean by crossing back is to say
就是說你回交的意思就是說
Rice, for example, has about 25,000 genes
譬如說水稻大概有25000個基因
that only
那其中只有
A small segment is the gene to resist leukemia
一小段是要抗白月骨病的基因
So if you teach Islam once, you will
所以你回教一次的話就是把
For example, I like Tainong No. 71 now
譬如說我現在喜歡台農71號
But I need the small piece of disease-resistant gene of Tainong 67
但是我需要台農67號那一小段抗病的基因
As soon as I teach, I will select the part of the gene that is resistant to the disease
我一教 那我就選抗病的那一段基因
That means I'll get about 75% once I crossbreed.
那說我雜交一次大概會有75%
It is probably possible to stay on Tainong No. 71
大概是可以留下來是台農71號
Only 25% are Tainong No. 67
只有25%是台農67號
But it's not real, isn't it fragrant rice?
但還不是真的 不是香米嘛
so you continue to muslim
所以你繼續回教
After a generation, it will reach about 95%
世代以後大概就到了95%
That's almost like turning into a basmati rice
那幾乎就是變成一個香米
You will be Muslim about five times later
你會回教大概五次以後
You will change from Tainong 67 to Tainong 71
你就會從台農67號變成台農71號
So it has been certified by the Council of Agriculture, that is to say
那所以在農委會已經鑑定就是說
The Tainong No. 71 that Mr. Wang taught in Islam
他王老師回教的這個台農71號
and a new strain
以及是一個新的品系
Available in about two years
兩年大概就可以上市
It's modified from a gray machine for anti-white frontal disease
就是抗白額骨病的灰機改的
Fragrant rice overflowing with wedding paper imperial seeds
用婚紙御種溢出來的香米
Then he is doing number 77 now
那他現在在做77號
So this is a
所以這個是一個
Works on very TDS
就非常TDS的工作
Because you can't spend money on this kind of paper
因為你不能花表這種論文
and to
而且要
you see everyone
你看各位
Muslim once a year
每年要回教一次
So it takes four to five years of hard work
所以就是要四五年的功夫
But here comes the fragrant rice
但是香米就來了
And without pesticides
而且不用農藥
but as i said before
但是我前面有講過
you have this
你有這個
Bacteria
續菌
Bacteria will follow and evolve
病菌他會跟著演化
Mr. Wang is now predicting this channel
王老師現在預出這個水道
If you don't help this channel
你如果沒有幫助這個水道
Anti-bacteria
抗病菌
maybe five years from now
也許五年以後
you have to do it again
你又要再來一次
Filter again
再來篩選
so
所以
The other half is my home
另外一半就是我的家
looking for
要找
to replace
要取代
Pesticides used by Kun Beibei
坤貝貝用的農藥
how do we find
我們要怎麼去找
now is
現在就是
In fact, in the soil
其實土壤中
There are also many microorganisms
也有很多微生物
They compete with each other in Vitality
他們維生物他徒朗中彼此競爭
So he often stunned and produced some compounds to kill other Seo Joon
所以他常常會昏迷出一些化合物殺掉別的敘俊
because he wants to compete he is in full circle
因為他要競爭他身處滿境
So a lot of Tulang's vitamins have coma compounds
所以很多的徒朗的維生物都有所昏迷化合物
Can be used as a biological machine
可以拿來當生物之機
Because he exists in nature
因為他是自然界就有的
He can use it to kill other Seo Joon
他可以拿來殺別的敘俊
So it was actually very difficult to find this kind of thing before.
所以以前找這種東西其實非常難
Often in five or ten years you still can’t find out what you saw
常常是五年十年你都還找不到到底是什麼看到
That's because the so-called genomics still has a lot of progress
那因為現在所謂的基因體學還有很多體學的進展
I'm talking to you now about a postgraduate student working for less than two years
我現在跟你講的是一個研究生不到兩年的工作
then we will find
那我們就找到
It's not that hard to find this way.
這個找的方法其實不是那麼難
That's when you smeared white leaf mushroom germs all over
那就是你把白葉菇病菌通通塗滿
inside this incubator
在這個培養機裡面
Then you dig a hole in the middle
然後你在中間挖一個洞
Then you take that Seo Joon you want to try
然後你把那個你要試的那個敘俊
Let's see if he has the ability to kill white leaf mushroom disease
看他有沒有殺白葉菇病的那個能力
the middle of the hole
這個洞中間
If he can kill Baiyan Bone Disease
那如果他能夠殺白顏骨病
He'll melt the white bone disease bacteria
他就會把白顏骨病菌融掉
He will come out in circles
他就會有一圈圈出來
then this is
那這個就是
Circle it, everyone, look at this
圈圈出來 各位看這個
Because he took pictures, this is the circle
因為他照相的關係 這個就是圈圈
Then you if this bacteria
那你如果這個菌
he doesn't have that ability
他沒有那個能力
Said that he himself cannot be degraded
說他自己就不能忽靡化物
Can't kill white face bone disease
不能殺掉白顏骨病
So this is the German style of what we call quick people
所以這種是我們所謂的quick人的德體
Now the problem is
那現在問題就是
you are going to find
你要去找
what compound
到底是什麼化物
Because you can't just say I'm an orderly
因為你不能只靠說我有序菌
Then my student
那我這個學生
designed a set
就設計了一套
That is
那就是
first step
第一步
just put this
就是把這個
this bacteria
這個序菌
He has the drug that kills the white bone disease
他具有那個殺白顏骨病菌的
He gave his whole order
他把他整個序給定出來
This bacterium is
這個序菌是
A teacher from Tamkang University, Wang Shanli
淡江大學一位王山里老師
He got out of the muddy mud of the Danshui River
他從淡水河的濫泥巴裡面
stuffed out
塞出來的
he originally wanted
他原先是想要
When he raised this bacteria
他當初養這個序菌的時候
It is to
是把
with shrimp shells
用蝦殼
When the only source of nutrients
當唯一的養混 淡的來源
He actually wanted to dissociate the lower shell.
他其實是想要做解離這個下殼的
Experiment to decontaminate Oh Han Jin
要做解除吳韓金污染的實驗
But hear it's a treasure
但是 聽到這是個寶
Because after my students tried
因為我學生試了以後
I found out that he has a lot of genes
發覺就是說他有很多基因
It seems that some secondary metabolites can be produced
好像可以產生一些二次代謝物
It can be used for sterilization
是可以拿來殺菌用的
So if you're looking for this compound early on,
所以那早期你要去找這個化合物的話
If you use the traditional method, it will be very painful
你用傳統的方法 那就很痛苦
Especially people in our lab like to make wedding paper creatures
尤其我們實驗室人都喜歡做婚紙生物
don't like chemistry
不喜歡化學
So you're going to the wedding to identify the structure.
所以你要去婚禮 要去鑑定那構造
That's a student in my lab
那是我實驗室的學生
definitely won't do it
絕對不會去做了
but with genetics you can do
但是有遺傳 你就可以做
Because we now know the sequence
因為我們現在知道這個序訊
about 1000 genes
大概有1000個基因
Then we have a technology that puts
那我們有一個技術就是把
What we call a carrier can
我們所謂的載體可以
It's your turn to insert it into the gene at will
輪等你隨意把它插到基因裡面
Then if you insert it into the gene
那你如果插到基因裡面
Genes cannot make normal proteins
基因就不能製造出正常的蛋白質
It looks like this...
這樣子它所...
If you insert the key gene
如果你插到關鍵基因
For example, I can kill albino frontal bacterium now
比如說我現在是可以殺白額孤病菌
Then you would generate this
那你會產生這個
Then if you...
那你如果...
this is you if that...
這個就是你如果那個...
If our gene is inserted into this gene called CLP
我們那個基因插到這個叫CLP基因的話
just look at it...
你看它就...
Its ability to integrate is not enough
它融進的能力就不夠
Then you insert these two genes
那你插到這兩個基因
the one of it won't blend in at all
它的那個根本就不會融進
So this one gives us a...
那所以這個就給我們一個...
a clue
一個線索
That is to say, the one that can kill the albino frontal bacterium...
就是說可以殺這個白額孤病菌的那個...
compound of
的化合物
maybe it has something to do with this
可能是跟這個有關的
That...
那...
My student he is very good
我那個學生他印氣非常好
Because at that time we had just killed a man from the United States
因為我們那個時候剛害了一個從美國
UC San Diego Wedding School Back
加州大學聖地牙哥婚校回來
it is a support instrument
它是做支撫儀
video support
叫做影像支撫儀
I think the technology of video support device is actually very simple
影像支撫儀我想技術其實很簡單
It's you who put Seo Joon here
就是你把敘俊放在這裡
Then Seo Joon will secrete
然後敘俊會分泌出來
Then you shoot the laser up
然後你把雷射打上去
That instrument is your laser
那支撫儀就是你把雷射
break down your compound into smaller molecules
把你的化合物打成比較小的分子
Then you can analyze its molecular weight
然後你就可以分析它的分子量
then use various compounds
那就用各種不同的化合物
then you can figure it out
那你就可以定出來
That is to say, it is inside the circle
就是說它這個圈圈裡面
how many compounds
到底有多少化合物
What is the molecular weight of its compound
那它的化合物的分子量是多少
Then you have this precise molecular weight
那你有了這麼精確的分子量
You can go back and find out what kind of nucleic acid it is
你就可以回去查到底是什麼樣的核酸
Then I told you again
那我前面又跟你講過
I have these mutants
我有這些突變種
it doesn't make these compounds
它不會製造這些化合物
So you compare what we say
所以你比較我們說的
WireTimes and these mutants
WireTimes跟這些突變種
you'll know soon
你就很快可以知道
What the hell is that nucleic acid?
到底是什麼那個核酸
can kill bone disease
可以殺掉排骨病
That's because
那因為
In terms of time, I will jump over quickly
時間的關係我就很快地跳過去
That is to say, my students are usually ordinary people
就是說我這學生通常平常人
About ten years, I think, about ten years of your skills
大概我想你以勞的技術大概十年
probably can make what he's doing now
大概可以做出他現在做的東西
Then he said less than two years
那他就說不到兩年
He found this compound
他就找出了這個化合物
It is the fungus next to the Danshui River I just mentioned.
就是我剛剛講的那個淡水河旁邊的菌
he can stun this compound
他可以昏迷這個化合物
he will spend silver light
他會花銀光
He can kill the white leaf mushroom ice fungus
他就可以殺掉白葉菇冰菌
it's a product of nature
這是一個自然的產物
And he produced a lot
而且他的產量還不少
so he now we have
所以他現在我們就有
We have Teacher Wang Qiangsheng
我們就有王強生老師的
The anti-bacteria of the white leaf mushroom ice of Mr. Wang Qiangsheng
那個王強生老師的抗白葉菇冰的菌
plus our compound
加上我們這個化合物
So my student ran to the Beiguo Farm of Chung Hsing University
所以我這學生就跑去中興大學的北國農場
do field experiments
做田間試驗
The field test is to use Honglaimi Tainong No. 6
田間試驗就是用紅萊米台農6號
Taichung No. 9 and Taichung First No. 10
台肯9號還有再來米台中先10號
Then you can see that this is
那你可以看到這是
It is the strength and weakness of the disease I showed you earlier.
就是我前面跟你們秀的那個病增的強弱
Then this is if you have been on Tainong No. 67, you can see that this is for curing diseases
那這個是如果你一直這個台農67號你看它這個是它治病的
Then you just need to spread the righteousness of our handsome
那你只要撒我們這個俊的那個上清義
It is more resistant to disease
它抗病的能力就多好多
So whether it is Tainong No. 67, Taycan No. 9, or Taichung Line to No. 10, it can be used
那所以不管是台農67號、Taycan9號還有台中線到10號都可以用
So we have this
那所以有了我們這個
Now we are talking with Xinnong to discuss whether it is how we want to mass produce
那我們現在在跟新農談就是要談是不是就是我們要怎麼樣去量產
Then with this creature, plus teacher Wang Qiangsheng’s anti-Baiyuegu disease waterway
那有了這個生物之際加上王強生老師的抗白月固病的水道
I think we have solved the problem of white moon solid disease in Taiwan in the next 10 or 20 years
我想我們解決了未來台灣10年、20年白月固病的問題
You don't need pesticides, just plant the anti-white moon disease water channel of Mr. Wang Qiangsheng
你可以不用農藥只要種王強生老師的抗白月固病的水道
Then at the right time, especially after Taiwan, you spread our Shangqing justice
然後在適當的時候尤其台灣過後你撒我們這個上清義
Probably no need for pesticides
大概就不需要用農藥
So this probably isn't
所以這個大概不是
that is
就是說
If it is to say that the direction of our research in the early stage of the Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine
如果就是說以中醫院早期的我們研究的方向
we probably wouldn't do this kind of question
我們大概不會去做這種問題
But because we are called agricultural biotechnology
但是因為我們叫做農業生技
if you go to that sky
如果你走到那個天間去
you will find that there are many problems
你就會發覺有很多問題
In fact, you can pay equal attention to applied and basic science
其實你可以應用跟基礎科學併重
This is a good example
這個就是一個很好的例子
The researchers at the Chinese hospital are not capable of doing all of them.
那中醫院的研究人員也沒有能力做所有了
You see our team actually has a neutral university
你看我們的團隊其實有中性大學
National Taiwan University, especially the department of agronomy
有台大尤其是農藝系的
There is also a farm
還有農事所
Not only did we do this
我們不只做了這個
This is just one of our seven sub-plans
這只是我們七個子計畫裡面
The existing achievements of the two sub-projects
兩個子計畫現有的成就
Teacher Qiu Zizhen's team
邱子貞老師的團隊
And teacher Cai Yifang's team
還有蔡宜芳老師的團隊
They actually found the same picture library inside
他們其實找到同樣的圖片庫裡面
find something called i cant call it a picture gallery
找到一些所謂我不能叫它圖片庫
new strain
就新的品系
You give him very little respite and he very little fade
你給他很少的靈回跟他很少的淡回
He looks just like you, give him a lot of flashbacks, a lot of flashbacks
他長得跟你給他很多靈回很多淡回
exactly as good
一模一樣好
So now they're working on
所以現在他們在研究
why did you give him so little fading
為什麼你給他這麼少的靈回淡回
he can look just as good
他還可以長得一樣好
This is actually a very difficult problem
這個其實是一個很困難的問題
But Teacher Qiu Zizhen and Teacher Cai Yifang are probably world-class
但邱子貞老師跟蔡宜芳老師大概是世界級的
two of the best scientists in plant nutrition
就是做植物營養的兩個最好的科學家
so i want to give them a few more years
所以我想再給他們幾年
It should be possible not only to say that it is practical
應該可以不只就是說有實用
can go to the fields
可以到田間去
It is also possible to understand the molecular mechanism
也可以了解這個分子機制
So to say I think I'm on this team I think we
所以說我想我對這個團隊我想我們
We can't say we've reached it
達到了我們當也不能說達到
In other words, I think our original idea
也就是說我想我們當初的idea
is to build a platform
就是要建置一個平台
so we can have a quick
讓我們可以有很快的
that has the ability to quickly produce new strains
那個有能力可以很快的產生出新的品系
So I gave a speech at the Council of Agriculture last month
所以我上個月在農委會演講
Speaking of Agricultural Economics
講農業經濟
is how you bring technology into this molecular domain
就是你如何用科技帶進這個分子域種
Then there is an expert from Japan
那日本那個有一個專家來
He said their plan now is to have vegetables or rice
他說他們現在的計畫是對蔬菜或水稻
They estimate if they have a letter of need to develop
他們估計如果他們有一個信狀需要發展
They do it about every three years
他們每三年大概就可以完成
The Mutual Aid Committee of the Council of Agriculture said whether we have the ability to do it
那農委會互助委說我們有沒有能力做
i think we have
我想我們有
but one thing is important
但有一點很重要
You need what's called a gene bank
你要有所謂的種緣基因庫
Because of the resistance I just mentioned
因為我剛剛講的那一些抗性
In fact, there are more or less in nature
其實在自然界多多少少都有
So why do you ask why biology makes sex important
所以你要為什麼生物都讓性很重要
It's that you have to keep the genetic pool of these resistances in the gene pool
就是你要保持這些抗性的種緣有基因庫在
then when you need
那你一旦需要的時候
You can go to the resistance genes that are already there in nature
你可以去那些自然界已經有的抗性的基因
You just smash it with the method of molecular domain
你就把它給用分子域種的方法砸掉
to what you need
到你所需要的
so why do we do
所以為什麼我們做
Although we are doing so-called biotechnology
雖然我們是做所謂的生物科技
You still have to support the so-called Bio-Diversity
你還是要支持所謂的Bio-Diversity
Because this is direction interlocking
因為這是方向相扣
you must have gene pool
你一定要有基因庫
The gene bank is Bio-Diversity
基因庫的話就是Bio-Diversity
Use the mutant gene pool with you
跟你用突變的基因庫
So why can we be so successful now
所以為什麼我們現在可以這麼成功
Because the farm has established a very good
因為農事所已經建立一個非常好的
That mutant library is over there
那個突變庫在那邊
And the waterway has a lot of natural ones
而且水道有很多自然界的那個
That mutant walks over there
那個突變走在那邊
So the channel is very thick
所以水道是很濃
Should be pretty easy now
現在應該算是相當容易
Can be used as wedding paper
可以做婚紙與宗
Most of that resistance has
大部分的那個抗性都有
That
那
So I guess it's almost time
所以我想時間差不多了
then i think
那我想
I listened to Shen Zheng Yuyan City last month
我上個月聽那個沈爭玉燕市
his that
他那個
There is a last era
有一段最後一張時代
i think i'm going to steal it and use it
我想我要把它偷來用
He said Taiwanese people are not afraid
他說台灣人沒在怕
say because of you
那就說因為你
you have a difficult problem
你碰到很困難的問題
you think you can't solve
你覺得你不能解決
He means you just need to put your mind to it
那他是說你只要用心什麼問題
With the waywardness of us Taiwanese, we must do it
以我們台灣人的任性一定做得出來
Although I have told you so much before
雖然我前面跟你們講的那麼多
our policy issues
我們政策性的問題
Easy policy seems to be messed up
容易政策好像亂七八糟了
a series of that is
一連串的那個就是
It is the evil law I mentioned earlier.
就是我前面講的叫惡法
But in fact those evil laws
但是其實那些惡法
The benefits of deferment aren't that bad
延先的利益並沒有那麼差
that now is to
那現在就是要
if we find a way
我們如果想辦法
be able to put these policies
能夠把這些政策
change it up a bit
把它稍微改一下
Let us plan the sustainable development of Taiwan's agriculture
讓我們規劃台灣農業永續發展
Average person goals and execution strategies
中常人目標還有執行策略
Then this must be driven by the government
那這個一定要政府帶動
because without the government
因為如果沒有政府帶動
you are really
你實在是
you with the power of the people
你以民間的力量
absolutely impossible
絕對不可能做出來
There must be a good government
一定要有一個好的政府
The second is the participation of the people
第二個就是人民的參與
The people are us, you and me
人民就是我們 也就是你我
I think many people have seen this question more or less in the newspapers.
這個問題我想很多人大概報紙多多少少都有看到
Like last month, some people protested against the constitutional government in Yilan
像上個月宜蘭憲政府有人抗議
Several teachers from Yilan University started to organize
宜蘭大學的幾位老師他們就開始組織起來
Hold forums and give speeches in various places in Yilan
就舉辦論壇 在宜蘭各地演講
If you can’t have only one voice in Taiwanese society
如果台灣的社會你不能只有這種一種聲音
Everyone should be able to organize
大家應該可以組織起來
Let the public know your ideas
把你的理念讓社會大眾也知道
I think this is the responsibility of us scholars in traditional Chinese medicine hospitals and everyone else.
我想這是我們這些中醫院的學者還有各位的責任
That is, you have to participate in this kind of social
就是你要參與這種跟社會
In fact, it cannot be called a problem that society is closely related to us.
其實不能叫社會跟我們息息相關的問題
Then why do I say Taiwanese
那為什麼我說台灣人
You are not afraid, because in fact our agricultural technology in Taiwan
沒有你怕 因為其實我們台灣的農業技術
World class at least so far
至少到現在為止還是世界一流的
It's just that we didn't integrate it
只是我們沒有把它整合起來
Everyone, if you look at the pumpkin industry
各位如果看看南瓜產業
know we didn't rely on
就知道我們沒有靠
In fact, we grow pumpkins
其實我們藝種 南瓜的藝種
And what about the pumpkin production line?
還有南瓜的生產線什麼
rarely rely on the government
很少靠政府
It's all our small farmers and some
都是我們那些小農還有一些
that pumpkin lover
那個南瓜的愛好者
I have to build it up slowly by myself to get to the current scale.
自己去慢慢弄起來才有現在的規模
Taiwan is now exporting Butterfly South for one year
台灣現在蝴蝶南一年出口
About four billion Taiwan dollars
大概四十億台幣
That feeds a lot of people
那這養活了不少人
And it won't happen suddenly
而且也不會忽然環境
what they did
那他們這些做出來的
Although some will be brought to the mainland by Taiwanese businessmen
在雖然有些會被台商帶到大陸
also hard to go
也很難去
But some skills cannot be learned
但是有些技術是學不來的
Because like the pumpkin now that link
因為像南瓜現在那個環節
by tissue culture
是靠組織培養
Taiwan's organization training is
那台灣組織培養都是
nothing happened in doing
沒有發生在做
not what you hire college students for
不是你聘大學生什麼
it is a production line
它就是一個生產線
rarely infected
很少感染的
big german family
德國一家很大的
multinational
跨國公司
go to vietnam to do
到越南去做
He also wants to follow the example of Taiwan
他也要效法台灣的
he built a big
他建立很大的
tissue cultured
組織培養的
he closed after three years
他三年以後就關了
because he can't
因為他沒有辦法
There is no way for the value of other functions
他功能的數值沒有辦法
In fact, tissue culture
其實組織培養
hard to say
說難不難
It's not easy to say
說簡單也不簡單
But the one in Taiwan
但是台灣的那個
Farmers also do these
農民還有從事這些
Agricultural Values
農業的數值
He just has his unique place
他就是有他獨特的地方
like our hurricane grapes
像我們的颶風葡萄
Everyone can know
各位可以知道
The ones grown in Taiwan are all good
在我們台灣種的都好
And now grapes
而且現在葡萄
all year round, right?
一年四季都有對不對
Grapes are actually seasonal.
其實葡萄本來是有季節性的
That's because our farmers in Taiwan
那就是因為我們台灣的農民
know when
知道什麼時候
with appropriate feedback
用適當的回料
You can adjust
可以調節
make it bloom
讓它促進它開花
that technology
那這個技術
already arrived
已經到了
Because they come to Taiwan to study
因為他們來台灣學
But they still can't make as good grapes
但是他們還是做不出一樣好吃的葡萄
Because of the problem of pests and diseases
因為還有病蟲害的問題
There is no country in the world where farmers
世界上沒有一個國家的農民
Have the patience to bag
有那個耐性去套袋
Guys, did you see that bag
各位你們看到那個套袋
he is a worker
他是人工人
If you ask mainland farmers to do it, they won’t do it
你大陸叫大陸農民做他不會做了
So why can we reduce pesticides
所以我們為什麼可以少農藥
make fruit that can be so beautiful
造成可以那麼漂亮的水果
because we farmers
因為我們農民
He not only has this technique
他不只有這個技術
There is still this patience that can be done
還有這個耐性可以做
So our
所以我們這個
Even though the day before yesterday on the front line
第一線的前天縱使
And to our research on agricultural technology
還有到我們農業科技的研究
We actually have a good chance
我們其實都有很好的利機
Now that's when we take advantage of it
那現在就是我們如果利用它
Then let us Taiwan's agriculture
然後讓我們台灣的那個農業
sustainable development
可以永續發展
ok i think i will stop here
好我想我就停在這裡
Thanks
謝謝
and i want to thank my team
還有我要謝謝我的團隊
It's definitely not my job alone
這絕對不是我一個人的工作
Thanks also to our Academia Sinica
還要謝謝我們中央研究院
Fellow Science Center support
同學科學中心的支持
There is also the Council of Agriculture and their investigation of the Agricultural Experimental Institute
還有農委會他們對農業試驗所
They are really very generous to us
他們對我們真的是非常慷慨
Whatever we use they are absolutely unconditionally fair
我們用什麼他們都絕對無條件公平
so it's very good
所以這是非常好的
I think it is a good platform
我覺得是一個很好的平台
because the whole is a joke
因為整體是誇笑
And the cooperation with Kua Unit
還有誇單位的那個合作
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
Thank you Director Shi
謝謝施主任
Very macro and micro
很宏觀也有微觀
sounds very exciting
聽來令人感到非常興奮
If you can't do it anymore, do you have any questions to ask him?
那麼再做不到有沒有什麼問題要請教他
Come
來
middle button
中間的按鈕
Thank you very much Mr. Shi for your wonderful speech
非常謝謝施老師的精采演講
We also learned a lot here
我們這邊也學了很多
In the Prime Minister's speech just now
總理剛剛的演講裡面
I probably have three
大概我個人有三個
As I said, the sustainable development of Taiwan is closely related to the loss of high-quality translations
說過 第一個 台灣的永續發展跟優質榮譯的流失有密切關係
The second zero profit and weakness of high-quality agricultural policy
第二個 優質的農業政策的零利跟弱勢
The third is the cultivation of high-quality talents and the education of a disadvantaged one.
第三個就是 優質人才的培育跟他的一個弱勢的一個教育
These three are actually related to a free relationship, that is, a person with talent.
這三個其實跟一個自由關係 就是人 人才的人
Here are two questions to ask Mr. Shi
在這邊提出兩個問題 請教一下施老師
first question please
第一個問題 請問一下
If your money is on May 20 next year, my colleague Dalin Hung
如果在明年5月20號你的錢 同仁 大林匈
If Luzumi Nakato has a third floor
如果陸組中戶有三樓的時候
What do you think is the market impact on the sustainable development of Taiwan's agriculture?
你認為對台灣農業永續發展的市面影響是什麼
The second question is do you have any way to influence your money, colleague Dalin Hung
第二個問題是 你有沒有辦法影響你這個錢 同事 大林匈
because we know his expertise is in public
因為我們知道他的專長在公共公共方面
game development for farming
對農業發展的遊戲 發展
What kind of positive impact can you put forward and provide him with advice, thank you
你能夠提出什麼樣的正面的影響 提供給他做意見 謝謝
right
對
ok i think i can answer one step
好 我想可以回答一步
i think chen hu is my immediate boss
我想陳護是我直接的老闆
I interact with him a lot
我跟他互動非常多
I believe he has a strong interest in the sustainable development of Taiwan's agriculture
我相信他對台灣農業永續發展
There must be a positive impact
一定會有正面的影響
Now it means
那現在其實就是說
we have a plan
我們有一個計畫
is helping with this
就是在幫助解決這個
the rural back state problem
那個回州的鄉郊的問題
Chen Hu is leading
就是陳護在主導
So he is concerned about agricultural issues
所以他對農業問題
know very well
知道得很清楚
So I think he will give
所以我想他一定會給
That is to say, if Tsai Ing-wen is elected
就是說如果蔡英文當選的話
he must be a good host
他一定會是一個很好的主持人
Then the second one will I have any influence
然後第二個我會不會有影響
then i will tell two stories
那我就講兩個故事
My wife heard that Chen Jianren was nominated for vice president
我老婆聽到陳建仁被提名的副總統
He said you stay away from him
他說你離他遠一點
Then the second is
然後第二個就是
I told Dean Li some of my methods
我跟李院長講了一些我這個方法
That is, how to enforce these policies
就是說如何執行這些政策
my wife said you go
我老婆說你去
Brass less than a month
不拉斯不到一個月
Dean Li said you don't get a week without Lars
李院長說你不拉斯得不到一個禮拜
so i think
所以我想
What I mean by this is
這個我要說的意思是說
need a comparison
需要一個比較
How can... a person like Chengwu
能夠怎麼...像成物這種人
he may stand
他才可能站在
we need a good
我們需要一個好的
Chairman of the Council of Agriculture
農委會的主委
but he needs to have
但是他需要有
Political School
Political School
Can manage our legislative chambers
可以Manage我們這些立法院
I think the biggest problem is the legislation
我覺得最大的問題就是立法
then this legislation
那這個立法
Then the administrative law I mentioned
那我說的那些行政法
Probably as long as you have a good county magistrate
大概你只要有好縣長
It is indeed possible to execute
確實是執行就可以了
but to get to the bottom of it
但是追根究底
You want a permanent agricultural basic law
你要有一個永久的農業基本法
that's probably
那大概就是
but our legislature
但是我們的立法院
In fact, I read the papers to propose bills.
其實是看報紙提法案的
So if you can be brave
所以如果各位可以勇敢的
not brave
也不是勇敢
Actively participate in this kind of worship
踴躍的去Participate在這種禮拜
you can disagree with me
你可以不同意我
But I think we're right about this...
但是我覺得我們對這個...
be more concerned
要多關心
because we've all heard the farmhouse problem
因為我們都聽到了農舍問題
but you rarely hear
但你很少聽到
There are people in Taipei who are openly discussing this issue
在台北有人在公開討論這個問題
So I think this is the participation of our society
所以我想這個就是我們社會大眾的參與
I think the most important
我覺得最重要
Because the Legislative Yuan almost relies on public opinion to govern the country
因為立法院幾乎是靠民意來治國了
so you just let them know it's an important issue
所以你就讓他們知道這是很重要的問題
people are paying attention
人民有在注意
to ask
來 問
I am New Deal Company
我是新政公司
My name is Lin
我姓林
hello please sit down
你好 請坐
ask now
現在請問一下
There used to be a Kaohsiung 131
以前有一個高雄131
This seems good too
這個好像也不錯
How does it compare to this
跟這個比是怎麼樣的
And our company has introduced this Ye Guangming
還有我們公司有引進這個葉光明
This is Yan Tian's
這個是嚴田的
farming
有農的
there is a peasant association
有一個農會
Everyone has peasant officials and citizens
大家就有農的官民
We introduce them
我們引進給他們種
and then this
還有再來是這個
There is Semite in California
加州有Semite那邊
there is a us taiwanese
有一個我們台灣人
their American company
他們美國的公司
He is Hong Xinxiong
他是洪信雄
he is a doctor
他是博士
where he produces people
他在那邊生產民
The rice on his side is called national defense rice
他那邊的米叫做國防米
It is given to Japanese geniuses every year
每年都送給日本天才用
I have lived in other homes several times
我有其他家住好幾次
this person is very nice
這個人是非常不錯
But he is also a doctor
不過他也是博士
Then there is a banquet in Japan recently
再來最近日本有一個宴祭
Water Pressure Yunmei
水壓雲美
This is inside our pentagon
這個是我們五角形裡面
Some here are good
有的這邊好
It's not good here, he's not, he's really good
這邊不好,他不是,他真的是通通好
I want to take his original seed, but he won't give it to me
我要拿他的這個原種,他不給我
He said, don't sell but fix
他說,不要賣也要固定
He became patented, not as easy as Moonlight Rice
他變成有專利,不像月光米那邊容易
So there's this synopsis aspect
所以裡面有一個這個協視方面
see what they do
跟他們做的看
this tastes good too, what
這個味道也好,什麼
Comfort, and this certificate, and this processing can all be done
舒適,還有這個證明,還有這個加工都可以
It seems that this favorite music is the best in Japan at present
目前日本好像這個最愛音樂是最棒的
This, sorry, I say this to
這個,對不起,我這樣講是要
I know, I know, thank you, thank you, because
我知道,我知道,謝謝,謝謝,因為
I think that there should be different strains in different places.
我想就說各地應該都有不同的那個品系
As for Moonlight Rice, there should be several strains in Taiwan
那至於月光米,台灣應該有幾個品系
One of the strains, if I remember correctly
其中有一個品系,如果我記得不錯的話
If you go to Japan, you should have won the moonlight rice
到日本去應該有贏過月光米
I won the moonlight rice in the previous year's competition last year
在去年來前年比賽贏過月光米
so they
所以他們
It's the weird rice you mentioned
是 你說的那些奇形怪狀的那個米
Mr. Wang Qiangsheng
那個王強生老師
i suggest you visit the farm
我建議你去農事所參觀一次
He planted all his mutant species over there.
他那邊把他的那個突變種通通種出來
Then you even saw the very one
那你甚至有看到那個非常那個
What do you guys appreciate most now?
各位現在大概最欣賞的就是什麼
Antioxidants?
抗氧化劑的嘛
There's the red one over there, and the paper one.
那邊有那個紅的 有紙的都有
So that mutation bank over there is really good.
所以他那邊那個突變庫非常好
Then you and him are also related
那你那個他也有關
Now their Council of Agriculture is also developing some rice
現在他們農委會也在發展一些水稻
come for viewing
要來當觀賞用
Because its leaf shape is very beautiful
因為他葉子形狀非常漂亮
Then I believe that if you plug carefully
那我相信你如果仔細去塞
It should be encouraged and there are beautiful ones
應該鼓勵也有很漂亮的都有
so it's a pity
所以很可惜
because if you come to my church last week
因為如果你上我上禮拜講
Because of the farm
因為農事所
The one celebrating his 120th anniversary this week and last weekend
這個週上個週末慶祝他120週年的那個所慶
So he got all his babies out
所以他把他所有寶貝都都出來
Exhibited in his farm
就在他農事所裡面展覽
That
那
we don't give him business
我們不要給他來做生意
OK, let me ask the Council of Agriculture again
好,我再問一下農委會
Because they usually have the one with the international waterway
因為他們通常如果有跟國際水道的那個
ok, we don't give it to us
可以,我們他不給我們
good
好
those two words
那兩個字
So Feast , Feast of Feast
所以宴,宴基的宴
Restraining harm is Yankee
戒害是宴基啊
Banquet
宴基
good
好
Okay, thank you
好,謝謝
ok, here you go
好,你來這樣
I charge a lot for your speeches
你的演講我收很多
but your final conclusion
不過你最後的結論
I feel like there is a contradiction
我覺得好像有矛盾
You said the government led the people to participate in
你說政府帶領人民參與
this is the first day
這是第一天
The second is whether you have talked about
第二個就是你有沒有談到
Orchids, lots of fruit
蘭花啦 很多水果
It's all made by the farmers themselves
都是農民自己做的
nothing to do with the government
跟政府沒有關係的
Aren't these two contradictory?
這兩個不是矛盾嗎
OK
OK
ours
我們那個
Okay, let's take orchids as an example.
好 就以蘭花這個例子
The output value of our orchids is 4 billion
我們蘭花四十億的產值
Compared with the electronics industry
你跟那個電子產業比
A piece of cake
不算什麼
When I came back in 2010
我2010年回來的時候
Back in 2008 2009
2008年回來 2009年
heard something
聽到一件事
Varma of America
美國的瓦馬
order
要訂單
Flower farmers in Taiwan
要台灣的花農
the one that supplies him with varmas all over america
供應他全美國瓦馬的那個
If we eat this order
如果我們吃了下這個訂單
That's about a few decades
那就幾十年大概就是
Our output value is definitely more than four billion
我們的那個產值絕對不只四十億
but why do we
但是我們為什麼
Because we are not an agribusiness
因為我們不是農企業
we are small farmers
我們都是小農
they may have some alliances
他們可能有一些聯盟
so i think
所以我想
First our government does not have one
第一個 我們政府沒有一個
What kind of venture capital fund do we have?
我們有什麼創投基金什麼的
We don't have an agricultural venture fund
我們沒有一個農業創投基金
Council of Agriculture asks the government
農委會要求政府
Asked for at least back from me
要求的至少從我回來
We meet every year at the Council of Agriculture
我們每年在農委會開會
we both say it takes
我們都說這個需要
just don't have this fund
就是沒有這個基金
Now there is a biomedical start-up fund
現在有生醫的創業基金
But there is no farming
但是就是沒有農的
so like this
所以像這種
to become an agribusiness
要變成農企業
I think it's still a government policy
我想還是要一個政府的政策
We want a school of appearance
我們要一個外貌的學會
So what we have now is wonderful
所以我們現在有的很精彩
correct
沒有錯
but you have to deal with the future
但是你要應付未來
i think there is still a problem
我想還是有問題
the second is
第二個就是
I said the government should drive
我說要政府帶動
Then compare the above policy aspects
那就比較上面的政策方面
allocation of land and water
土地 水資源的分配
i think this has no government
我想這個沒有政府
It's useless for you to do it tomorrow
你明天做沒有用
I'm talking about government-led
這個我說政府主導
we are involved in this
我們參與是在這個方面
you want to be big
你就要公大張
No, I mean that the first item and the second item you mentioned just now are contradictory
不是 我是說你講的剛才第一項跟第二項是有矛盾的
Yeah
對 對 對
I totally agree with your first item that the government leads the people to participate
對 你講的第一項說政府帶領人民參與我完全同意
That is, our government does not pay much attention to agriculture at present.
就是目前我們政府是對農業不重視
It is the carving of faces in rural areas that creates many, many problems
是農村雕臉的產生很多很多的問題
uh-huh
嗯哼
The funding for the research units of the agricultural institute you mentioned is not enough.
那個你講的農事所這些研究單位經費也不夠
right
對
Many comparative research centers are also shrinking
很多相較研究中心也在收縮
All the things in the research center are gone
乾脆研究中心所有的東西已經沒有了
right
對
So you say the government leads the people to participate in
所以你說政府帶領人民參與
This may have a higher class
這個可能有更高的階層
That is, we want a good government, good representatives of public opinion, good representatives of public opinion
就是我們要好的政府好的民意代表好的民意代表
or else
不然就是
In my idea, the government should be a good government
在我的idea裡面政府應該都是好的政府
But there are always times of disappointment
不過總是有失望的時候
right
對
ok
ok
Occidental, personal matters are subject to thank you
歐美士 私事要受謝謝你
i want to ask two questions
我想請教兩個問題
The first is that you just mentioned that
第一就是你剛剛有提到說
In terms of waterways
以水道來講
backcross
它預總的時候它的回交
this will take four years
這個要四年
Then if in terms of genetic modification
那麼如果在基改方面
can shorten the period of this backcross
能夠縮短這個回交的年限
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
the second is
那第二就是
Like the new varieties we pre-assessed
像我們預總出來的新品種
That one is made in the improvement factory
那那個是在改良廠裡面做
it's just a handful
它只是一小撮
I am always thinking
我一直在想
how does it expand to
它怎麼擴大到
Let the whole province's rice be replanted
讓全省的稻米去再種
how did this expand
這是怎麼擴大出來的
OK
OK
i think in general
我想一般而言
if you understand
如果你了解
For example, what are we going to fight against?
比如說我們要抗什麼
anti-what mechanism
抗什麼的機制
you usually just want
你通常就是要
Do 10,000 basic research first
要先做一萬基礎研究
Then after knowing the mechanism
然後知道了那個機制以後
which gene do you know
你知道哪個基因
Of course you have this basis in the future
當然你有的這個基礎以後
do genetic modification
做基改
much faster in some crops
在某些作物會快很多
But not now for waterways
但對水道而言現在不見得
Because rice, for example, if I just want to find
因為水稻 譬如說我如果只是要找
Rice is the same as rice because it has many species
水稻跟水稻的話 因為它的種原多
So it has this resistance
所以它這個抗性的都有
So it's not that you have to do genetic modification
所以它你要做基改也不是
That is to say, after you enter, we call it T1, the first generation
就是說你進去以後 我們叫做T1 就第一代
You can't use the first generation because it's actually mixed
你第一代不能用 因為它其實是混雜了
You have fortified for generations
你要塞了好幾代
So genetic modification is not available in the first generation
所以基改也不是第一代就能用
i know what you mean
我知道你這個意思
Of course the GMO will be irreplaceable at some point
當然基改會在某些時候是不能取代的
because you have like a banana
因為你有像香蕉
Bananas you can't do crossbreeding
香蕉你就不能做雜交
Bananas reproduce asexually
香蕉是無性繁殖的
So you have to improve its traits
所以你要改善它的性狀
The fastest you can do it with GM bananas
你最快的就是用基改香蕉來做
so you
所以你這個
My felacephy is to say
我的Felacephy是就是說
when possible
when possible
you use monocular breathing
你用monocular breathing
that is if possible
就是說如果可能的話
when necessary
when necessary
when you must
你一定必須的時候
use genetic energy
用genetic energy
Personally, I absolutely believe that genetic modification is very safe.
這個我個人是絕對相信基改做非常安全
But because it's not already a scientific question
但是因為這不是已經不是科學問題
it's a political issue it's a social issue
這是政治問題這是社會問題
So you are here to take our scientist's point of view
所以你在這以我們科學家的觀點
you have to solve the problem
你要解決問題
And you have to be able to make it easy for ordinary people to accept
而且你要能夠讓一般老百姓很快接受
So the fastest way is to use monocular breathing
所以最快的方法就是用monocular breathing
Everyone wouldn't have that pattern
大家就不會有那模式
But genetically modified things must be done
但是基改做物是絕對要做的
because you have many places
因為你很多地方
You can't do it with a traditional molecule
你用傳統的一種分子一種絕對做不出來
so here is my opinion
所以這是我的看法
There is also a second question
還有第二個問題是
What is done and then given out after
什麼是做物再給出來之後
how can you do it
你做得到什麼樣的方法
Our Council of Agriculture has a
我們農委會有一個
It is our Taiwan agriculture
它這個是我們台灣農業
That is to say, a place where the agricultural system is very complete
就是說農業系統非常完整的地方
they will
他們會
So the farm reform factory is in direct contact with the farmers
所以農改廠是直接跟農民接觸的
Then everywhere they will know
然後在每一個地方他們會知道
Rice will grow better in this place because of its water and soil
在這個地方因為它的水土什麼水稻會長得比較好
Therefore, the agricultural reform factory will recommend farmers
所以農改廠會推薦農民
That is to say, you go to plant a strain
就是說你去種來一個品系的
So why are the Taiwan stalks planted on Chishang?
所以為什麼池上那邊種的是台梗幾號
And now most of the west coast plants are Tainong No. 71
然後西海岸現在種的大部分都是台農七十一號
So there are agricultural reform factories that are responsible for these aspects
所以是有農改廠在負責這些方面
So we have the Council of Agriculture and this kind of policy of withdrawal
所以我們是有農委會是有這種退廣的政策
and always
而且一直都在
so the system is very good
所以這個系統非常好
ask that
請教那個
consult
請教
Spars
斯伯士
I just heard you say that machine modification is safe? Is it true?
那個剛剛聽到你說機改安全真的嗎
I am afraid that the so-called tofu will be broken
我怕的那個機改所謂豆腐都會不
Dare to eat it? Is it really safe?
敢吃了 真的可以吃嗎 真的安全嗎
Actually you
其實你
Because of genetic modification, everyone is afraid that you have introduced foreign genes, right?
因為基改大家怕是說你引進外來的基因對不對
do you eat flour
那你吃不吃麵粉
do you know where that wheat comes from
你知道那個小麥從哪裡來的
do beans matter
豆有關係嗎
without me talking about flour first
沒有我先講麵粉
wheat you know
小麥你知道
He is an extended species but he introduced
他是一個延伸種但是他引進了
Didn't know there were three different breeds of genes
不知道有三個不同的品種的基因
So he's a mix of a lot of alien genes
所以他是一個混雜的很多外來基因
So the genetically modified crops are actually just introducing a
所以基改作物他其實只是就是說引進一個
a foreign gene or two
一兩個外來基因
Well, in fact, you don’t need to look at the genes of all genetically modified foods.
那其實所有的基改食品你不是要看基因
but to look at the safety of his food
而是看他食品的安全性
not only
那不只
All countries Taiwan also has a very strict system called
所有的國家台灣也有一個非常嚴謹的叫做
Food Safety Inspection
食品安全檢驗
All foods to be marketed for practicality
所有要上市實用性的食品
have to go through a series of safety tests
都要經過一連串的安全性實驗
Until now
到現在為止
None of the genetically modified
沒有一個基改的
The soy you are talking about and the genetically modified corn
你講的大豆還有基改的玉米
so there will be insecurity
所以會有不安全性
and even if you talk about corn
而且甚至如果你講玉米的話
Genetically Modified Corn Is Likely Safer
很可能基改玉米更安全
because I promise you if you buy corn
因為我保證你如果買了玉米
It will be genetically modified without that insecticide
會基改的沒有那個蟲藥
or a mess
或者是亂七八糟
I guarantee you have eaten pesticide
我保證你吃進了農藥
Much more than genetically modified
比基改的要多很多
so you can eat with confidence
所以可以放心吃
I think you've been eating for a long time
我想你已經吃了很久了
because Taiwan
因為台灣
i told you earlier
我前面跟你講
Taiwan does not import
我們台灣不進口
do not produce soybeans themselves
自己不生產大豆
We import without fainting
我們進口沒有昏縮
You import genetically modified soybeans
你進口的要基改大豆
GMO soybeans
會基改大豆
We are not such imports
我們不是這樣的進口
We import is faint
我們進口是昏縮
It depends on his quality, from level one to level ten
就看他的品質 一級到十級
Then when we grain merchants come in
那我們這些糧商進來以後
He doesn't care if you are genetically modified or will be genetically modified
他就也不管你是基改 會基改
He started to sell and used the top-level ones as practical
他就開始賣 把頂級高的拿來當實用
The top low ones are used as animal feed
頂級低的拿去做動物飼料
So any soymilk shop, tofu shop, or even Yiyimi
所以任何豆漿店 豆腐店 甚至義以米
I also told you that he will be genetically modified.
也跟你講了說他是會基改的
he lied to you
他騙你的
he definitely lied to you
他絕對是騙你的
because you can't avoid
因為你沒有辦法避免
Because Taiwan does not produce
因為台灣不生產
The corn you eat, I guarantee you 100% GMO
那你吃的玉米 我保證你百分之百會基改
because i told you earlier
因為我前面跟你講
Because imported genetically modified corn
因為進口的基改玉米
you will never eat
你絕對不會吃
because it is hard and unpalatable
因為它又硬又難吃
what you eat what you eat is called
你吃的 你所謂吃的叫做
Sweet Cone
Sweet Cone
corn of utility
是實用性的玉米
Taiwan is 100% self-produced
台灣是百分之百自己生產
so you should be more careful
所以你反而要小心一點
Because there are many pesticides
因為農藥很多
Because corn can easily cause that
因為玉米很容易引起那個
and
而且
So you are something like this instead
所以你反而是這種東西
you have to wash very
你要洗得很
soy milk is very safe
豆漿是很安全的
And I promise you GMOs
而且我保證你基改食品
he eats naturally
他吃得自然
do you drink soy milk
你喝不喝豆漿
drink
喝
I can't drink now
現在快不敢喝了
I
我
ah
呀
here
這邊
good
好
hello host
這主持人您好
thank you very much for your speech tonight
非常謝謝您今晚的演講
It is true that there is a lot of harvest
也是的確收穫量多
and say you are
並且說您在
See Sustainability Issues Inside
看到永續發展的問題裡面
Because it includes the part of food security
因為包括糧食安全這個部分
include
包括
If we say Chinese is food security
如果我們說中文是糧食安全
Only two words of safety
只有安全兩個字
But if it's in English
但是如果是英文方面的話
Security and Safety issues
Security跟Safety的問題
you have discussed
您都有探討到
So my question is actually
所以我問的問題其實
Director Shi has already answered half of the answer just now
剛剛施主任已經回答了一半
Because you just mentioned that
因為剛剛您有提到的是
What we're about to do is
我們即將進行的是
A second-generation green revolution
一個二代綠色革命
because we were in the 1960s
因為我們在1960年代的
During the first green revolution
第一次的綠色革命的時候
At that time, it was only for the purpose of increasing food production.
當時只為了說要提高糧食的產量
The extensive use of fertilizers and pesticides
而大量使用肥料跟殺蟲劑
but did not consider saying
可是並沒有考慮到說
Problems that follow include pollution
後面帶來的問題是包括汙染
and subsequent generation of some
以及後續的產生一些
Farmer's Health Issues
農民健康的問題
The Second Green Revolution
這個二代綠色革命
words in your opinion
在您看來的話
because it involves
因為它的牽涉到
also includes bringing a little bit of genetic modification and
也是包括帶到一點基因改造以及
Some more general effects
一些比較全面性的影響
What you just mentioned is that
那剛剛您提到的是說
May reduce dosage
可能減少用量
Reduce environmental pollution
減低對環境的污染
But say whether to consider saying
但是說是否考慮到說
If this goes on for a long time in the future
未來這個長期進行下來的話
will there be
會不會有
Speaking in a big environment
在大環境來說的話
Will it be friendly to the environment?
會不會對於友善環境方面
Will there be some negative impact
會不會有一些負面的影響
including species diversity
包括說物種多樣性
Or those related effects that become harmful
或是說變成害的那些相關的影響
Thanks
謝謝
i want to answer this question
我想回答這個問題
Avision is relative
Avision is relative
Do you think genetically modified crops will affect biodiversity?
你說做基改作物會不會影響生物多樣性
my answer is yes but
我的答案是yes but
as long as i feel
只要我覺得
Since humans have agriculture
自從人類有農業以後
as long as you have agricultural land
你只要有農業的地帶
no biodiversity
就沒有生物多樣性
Because in nature you don't see
因為自然間你不會看到
ten thousand rice fields
一萬無計的稻田
rice field
稻米田
ten thousand cornfields
一萬無計的玉米田
Then your agriculture for thousands of years in the past few years
那你這幾年內幾千年的農業
The one that went through pesticides and recycling
再經過農藥、回料的那個
Your biological delusions have already
你生物的妄性早已經
where people are gone
有人的地方都不見了
So if you say that I plant now
那所以你如果說我現在種
This genetically modified vaccine is here
這個基改疫苗在這個地方
Will it affect the delusion of creatures
它會不會影響生物的妄性
you don't exist anymore
你本來就不存在了
Because it has been followed by our human behavior
因為已經被我們的人類的跟作行為
Your biological arrogance has long since been destroyed
你生物的妄性早就破壞
Then you have to modify this gene
那你要把這個基改的做
If planted in the mountains
種到山裡面去的話
of course i will affect
我當然會影響
But you plant ordinary waterways into the mountains
但是你把普通的水道種到山裡面去
You will affect your ecology as usual
你照常會影響到你的生態
so i think
所以我想
That is to say, when you all look at this matter
就是說你所有看這個事情的時候
I think you must read relative
我想一定要看 relative
That is to say, you are comparing it with the existing agriculture
就是說你是跟現在現有的農業來比較
What are genetically modified crops?
基改作物是怎麼樣
then i can talk to you
那我就可以跟你講
it is definitely safer
它絕對是比較安全
And it does less damage to the environment
而且它對環境的破壞比較少
I don't know if this answers your question
不知道這樣有沒有回答你問題
OK
OK
Wang Mu
王牧
It's the director. Just now you mentioned the problem of waterway febrile disease.
是主任 剛才你提到有關水道溫孤病的問題
Then why the previously collected disease strains are relatively complete
那為什麼以前收集的病菌株比較齊全
then almost none now
那現在幾乎就沒有
Is it because the brain farmer has used up the opportunity for technology research
是不是因為腦農民進把技術研究的機會用掉了
No, this has something to do with our agricultural policy
不是 那這個跟我們也是跟農業政策有關係
Didn't we talk about getting some of our
我們在有一陣子不是說要把我們的一些
Humanization of government research units
政府的研究單位化人化
In that era, there were many soups
在那個時代 有很多台湯啊
And the Banana Research Institute mentioned by Dean Li
還有李院長提到的那個香蕉研究所
And the county and city agricultural office, our agricultural cover merchant
還有那個縣市農事所 我們農蓋商
Many excellent researchers and agricultural talents
很多優秀的研究人 農作人才
First-line research talents
一線的研究人才
Move to early retirement or speak badly
移得提早退休 或者是講不好
This decade happens to be in turmoil
這個十年剛好就是在動蕩
it's them who are in turmoil
就是他們在動蕩不安
To be changed to Cai Tang Chinese
要改成蔡湯華人
When a lot of people can't surrender
一大堆人降不暴的的時候
Because if you want Cai Tang Chinese
因為要蔡湯華人的話
So he wants to use Taitang's point of view
所以他就是要以台湯的觀點
He wants to make a profit
他是要盈利為主
so he
所以他就
He actually has a Taiwan soup
他其實有一個台湯
In fact, our sugar industry in Taiwan
其實是我們台灣的糖業
he is the kingdom
他是王國
But then I stopped planting this kind of sugar
但後來不種這糖了
We have a lot of species
我們有非常多的種原
the candy is gone
這糖的不見了
are now in Guangxi
現在都在廣西
Our Nanhua has many kinds of origin
我們南華有很多種原
gone now
現在也不見了
because
因為
Just say Cai Tanghua
就說蔡湯華
They feel that they will be humanized by Cai Tang
他們覺得要被蔡湯華人化
not national
不是國立的
he won't do it
他就不做了
researchers are
研究人員才是
so i said
所以我說了
The collection of physiological data
那生理小總的收集
That decade happened to be
那十年剛好就是
rock the boat
搖船
In fact, some people said that Cai Tang should be Chinese
其實有說要蔡湯華人化
but then it didn't work out
但是後來沒有成功
because of too much resistance
因為阻力太大
But these ten years
但這十年
It's the time when the physiological summary has not been collected
就是生理小總沒有收集的時間
That
那
luckily
很幸運的就是
Liu Dajiang
前任的所長劉大江
And the current director once went in
還有現任的所長曾進去
attach great importance to this
對這個都非常重視
so we start again now
所以我們現在又開始
Go to various locations in the former province to start collecting
到前省各地點開始收集
Then Chiayi divides all diseases
那嘉義分所有個病普
He is in the special city every year
他就每年在專門市
So now we are also working on the division of labor
所以我們現在分職的也有在做
Traditional physiological niches are also doing it now
傳統的生理小眾現在也有在做
this right
這個對
That is to say, I think I should go down later.
就是說我想應該以後就會下去
because it will be inherited
因為會傳承這樣
I am also a member of the Academia Sinica
我也是中央研究院的議員
This is also the owner of this city
也是這個市主人的這個
Member of the Agricultural Center
農生中心的議員
I have two words that I want to share with you
我有兩個話想要跟大家Share
the first is
第一個就是
Just now the mayor said
剛才市主人說
our farmers in taiwan
我們台灣的農民
This high level is the highest level in the world
這個高水準全世界高水準
Dean Li also said just now
那剛才李院長也說了一下
His is just a half-open small comment
他的就是半開完小的一些comment
I will share with you
我跟大家Share一下
three things
三個事情
Taiwanese farmers
台灣的農民在我回國的
When participating in the Agricultural Center
參加農生中心的時候
A Mr. Cai called and said you want to come and see
有一位蔡先生打電話來說你要來看
How is our Nanhua planted?
我們這個南華是怎麼種的
When I went down, I went down with three colleagues in the firm.
我下去的時候跟所裡面三個同事一起下去
What I saw was this factory that was about five times bigger than this room
我看到的是比這間屋子要大大概五倍的這個廠房
There is a ditch in front
前面是一個水溝
Make it impossible for ordinary cars to enter
使得車子普通不能進去
There are wolf dogs in it
裡面養了狼狗
He said that you people who engage in learning never want to
他說從來你們這些搞學問的人就不想
look down on us
看不起我們
I'll show you today what we look like
我今天給你看一看我們是什麼樣子
all his techniques
他那個所有的技術
Because I participated in it when I was abroad
因為我在國外的時候參加過
Monsanto's so-called most of the research work and so on
孟山都的所謂的大多的研究工作等等
I see their tissue culture
我看他們的組織培養
really world class
真的是世界一流
But they say we go abroad
可是他們說我們到國外去
When we came to the Dutch people, they regarded us as bounty soldiers.
到荷蘭人家都把我們當作賞兵
Now to Taiwan we come back
現在到台灣我們回來
You are all in college
你們這些都是在大學
nothing never comes
都是什麼都從來不來
come see us
來看我們
really very embarassing
真的是很embarassing
just feel ashamed
就是覺得很慚愧
their technical system, etc.
他們那個技術的系統等等
still there today
今天還在那邊
so many feathers of our blue flower
那好多我們的藍花的羽種
under such circumstances
都是在那樣子的環境下
Now that is called seed fate is still there
現在那個叫做種緣也還在那裡
Not only that, it's just a blue flower
不但如此 這只是藍花
Our Taiwan is the one that makes that fish in the world
我們台灣是世界上做那個魚的那個
called invitro fertilization
叫做invitro fertilization
in vitro fertilization
就是叫做體外受精
also very powerful
也很厲害的
We in Taiwan can make that grafted plant
我們台灣可以做那個嫁接的植物
Even the bean sprouts can be grafted
連那個豆苗也可以做嫁接
So we have these awesome systems
所以我們有這麼厲害的一些系統
But it sounds like arguing
可是呢好像爭執聽起來
Our government doesn't care
我們的政府也不太管
everyone buried there
大家都埋沒在那裡
Another one is
另外一個就是
I've been thinking about it for a while
我想一段時間了
Our Agricultural Center
我們農生中心
very myself personally at least very anxious
非常我自己個人至少非常著急
We don't seem to have done a single agricultural thing
我們好像都沒有做到一件農業的事情
Even if you want to do it, you can't do it well
想做也做得不好
Also since this psychological
也是自從這個心理化
Since the benefactor came
自從這個施主人來了以後
several years
幾年間
five or six years
五六年間
get the system out
把這個系統弄出來了
Everyone saw it today
今天大家也看到了
so i feel
所以我自己就覺得
I won't panic like that
我不會那麼樣子的panic
OK would not feel like saying
OK 就不會覺得說
what happened
怎麼搞的
It seems to be these two
好像是這兩個呢
for your reference
是供大家參考
Thanks
謝謝
Yes, our government is doing something
有啦 我們政府有在做事
that's me
那就是我
Government’s BTC this year
政府在今年的BTC
That's the one
就是那個
Every year the government organizes a
每年政府會開一個
biotechnology summit
生物科技的高峰會議
Then I told the Council of Agriculture
那我跟農委會的
Director Lu Wusheng
魯武生處長
then we will
那我們會
Together we have planned a
我們共同規劃了一個就是
The future is the next five or ten years
將來的就未來五年十年的
so-called systems biology
把所謂的系統生物協
The general description of bringing high technology to Taiwan
開高科技帶進台灣的那個總描
Then we lock the top ten
那我們鎖定的十大
The top ten general descriptions of Taiwan are
台灣十大總描就是
We use in Taiwan
我們台灣用的
then also
然後也是
Top 10 general descriptions of our competitiveness in the world market
對我們在世界的市場有競爭力的十大總描
We are going to introduce new technology
我們要引進新的技術
Establish a so-called industry-government-university-research alliance
成立一個叫做所謂的產官學研的聯盟
researchers from Academia Sinica
就是從中研院的研究人員
university researchers
大學的研究人員
From farmers to farmers we all have a link
到農民我們中間都有一個環節
The Committee of Agriculture of this meeting and request has been sent out
這個經會和request的農委會已經送出去了
But that is the next year's meeting
不過那個是後年的經會
so i think probably not
所以我想大概不會過
because of the change of dynasty
因為要改朝換代
maybe next year again
也許明年再重新提過
But I think we've planned
不過我想我們已經規劃好了
so there is doing
所以是有在做
This is one about the bioeconomy
這是一個就是有關生物經濟的
Another COA has planned a project called Productivity 4.0
另外一個農委會規劃了一個叫做生產力4.0
That is to put the so-called big data
那就是把那個所謂的大數據
And that modern manage management approach
還有那個現代的manage management方法
To get flower show agribusiness
要弄到花展農企業
so someone is doing it
所以是有人在做
so now you have a plan
那現在就是你有了規劃
someone has to do it
要有人去執行
This is very important
這個很重要
yes i want not only in the middle
是我想不只在中間
Central Plains I want to be in college at COA
中原我想在大學在農委會
there are still many scientists
還是有很多科學家
and these executives
還有這些行政人員
everybody wants to do something
大家想要做一點事
that's why i say this
所以我才會說這個
That's why I'm still quite optimistic
這個就是我還是蠻樂觀的
I am optimistic by nature
我天生就是樂觀
So I think there will still be improvement
所以我覺得還是會有改善
Li En is
李恩是
it's okay lee
李恩沒關係
Thanks
謝謝
ok please
好 請
that just mentioned
那個剛才有提到說
We have some that can be biologically controlled
我們有那個可以用生物防治的一些
When producing organisms to resist that germ
生產生物之際來抵抗那個病菌
that could reduce our use of pesticides
那可以減少我們農藥的使用
So how to do a promotion of these
那如何來做這些的一個推廣
And how to study the classics
還有如何在研究的經會上
if go for it
如果去爭取
This may be a major feature we are facing
這可能就是我們要面臨的一個大特點
Yes, this is actually ours should be from last year
對 那這個就是其實我們的那個應該是去年的
It is the Council of Agriculture that plans our country's major agricultural research topic in the next ten years
就是農委會就是規劃我們國家未來十年這個農業重大的研究議題
One is the time of living beings and the other is the time of living beings
有一個就是生物之際 有一個就是生物之際
If you go back and read the report from last year
你如果回去看去年的那個報導
So there will probably be more or less the experience of this aspect coming out.
那所以大概會多多少少會有這一方面的那個經會出來
In fact, many people in Taiwan are now doing so-called biological research
其實台灣現在已經不少人在做所謂的生物之際研究
But it's a pity it's only half done
但是很可惜的就只做到一半
Because they often find useful bacteria
因為他們常常找到有用的菌
In fact, if you go to Taiwan carefully to find out about that
台灣其實你如果仔細去去去涉取一下那個
Because Mr. Wu and I are in charge of the so-called national research program in Taiwan.
因為我跟吳老師我們有管那個我們台灣的那個所謂的那個類似國家研計劃的
Then you know that there are many useful bacteria
那你就知道有很多很有用的菌
also know what he can cure
也知道他可以治什麼
but can't leave the country
但出不了國
because they didn't make it like we did
因為他們沒有像我們把它做到
That is to say, what are you like other than identification?
就是說你除了鑑定是怎麼樣的
The structure of this compound
這個化合物它的構造
You also need to know how it is synthesized
你還要知道它怎麼合成
you need to know under what circumstances
你要知道在什麼狀況之下
it can be mass produced
它可以大量生產
because the lotus i visited
因為我訪問的那個蓮花
It is the great merchant of the biological order
它是生物之階的大商
It has a ton or two of flower yeast sticks
它有一兩噸的花酵杖
You have to be competitive
你要有市場競爭力
You just want a ton of production costs
你就是要一噸的生產成本
The training machine costs 1,400 Taiwan dollars
那個培養機要1400塊台幣
But we use in the lab
但是我們在實驗室用
probably more than ten thousand yuan
大概不只一萬塊
that is to say if you want a ton
就是說你要一噸的話
so this down
所以這個下來
That is, you have to continue to do it
就是你還要再繼續做
Many teachers in Taiwan now have training
台灣現在很多老師都有訓
But the problem is you don't know the mechanics of it
但是問題是你不知道它的機制
you don't know what condition it is in
你不知道它在什麼狀況
This bacteria will produce the compound you want
這個菌會產生你要的化合物
often the first generation is useful
常常第一代有用
Farmers go back to raise themselves
農民回去自己養
or your company do it yourself
或者是你公司自己做
Often the second generation is useless
常常第二代就沒有用
So many big factories
所以很多大廠
Like Xinlong and Lianhua
像新隆還有蓮華
they came out
他們出來了
farmers scold
農民就罵嘛
Because you sell it seems to be useful for the first year
因為你賣好像第一年有用
useless in the second year
第二年就沒有用
It's the comparison you want to do scientifically.
就是你要科學要做的比較殺
this is the most important
這個最重要
don't worry
不要急
If you know the mechanism
你要是知道的機制
what companies do you know
你知道什麼companies
You can go abroad with Quality Control
你可以Quality Control就可以出國
So like our white jade archaea
所以像我們這白玉古病菌
The patent we are applying for now is
這個我們現在申請的專利是
Mainland China America
中國大陸美國
We just want to connect the Asian market with the US
我們就是要搭亞洲市場跟美國
So back to Dean Li's words
那所以回到李院長的話
What does this government do?
那這個政府做哪一些
help us open the way
幫助我們打通路
we have a foreign trade association
我們有一個外貿協會
But they won't do it for farmers
但他們不會幫農的做
do this
做這件事
So this is where the government can focus
所以這就是政府可以著力的地方
There are actually many details
那其實就有很多細節
I didn't speak
我沒有講
I'm on this policy today
我今天是在這個政策方面
but many implementation aspects
但是很多執行方面
You are still a place where the government can focus
你還是政府可以著力的地方
still so much
還是會那麼多
The key is to have money
關鍵是要有錢
So the first thing is to delete the 50 billion Laolong annuity
所以第一個就是要把老龍年金500億刪下來
your last question first
你先最後一個問題
Thanks
謝謝
You mentioned a very serious problem in Taiwan
你提到台灣的一個很嚴重的問題
It's food citizens' problem
就是糧食的公民的問題
Only 30% of myself
自己只有30%
this is very low
這個是非常低的
Of course, improving the variety of Dao species is a very important way
當然改良道種的品種是一個很重要的途徑
Do you want to consider other than rice
是不是要考慮除了稻米以外
Species such as Potato
種譬如說Potato
or something else to increase Taiwan's food supply
或是其他來增加台灣糧食的供應
I remember when Wang Guoren was renting an apartment years ago
記得肉乾年前王國仁還在租所的時候
he's doing it
他就在做這方面
At that time, I was also developing this aspect
當時我也是發展這方面
have no idea
不知道
Because now we eat more than just rice
因為現在我們吃的不只是稻米
Some people eat very little rice now
有人現在米都吃得很少
changed to face
改成麵
these grains
這些糧食
Should it also be considered
是不是也是應該考慮
these issues
這幾個方面的問題
Yes, this is actually 30 meters
對 這個其實那個30米
is absolutely enough
是絕對夠
I count 30%
我算個30%是說
The heat we design
我們所設計的熱量
70% are medium
70%是中
That is to say where the food comes from
就是說那些食物來的來源
70% are from outside
70%是外面來的
So your most important thing to solve
所以你最重要要解決的
actually bones
其實是骨類
the Council of Agriculture
那農委會
In fact, we in Taiwan had soybeans in the early days
其實我們台灣早期有種大豆
that's in taiwan
那在台灣
In fact, natural gas is not suitable for planting
其實天然的氣又不適合種
other bone species
種其他的骨類
rice is natural
水稻是天然的
But neither soy nor sorghum
但是大豆這個高粱都不
but we have a pre-release for a while
但是我們有一陣子有預出
soybeans that can be grown in taiwan
可以在台灣生長的大豆
But you have to pre-produce new varieties
但是你要預出新的品種
To be able to really push out the plant
要能夠真的推出去種
Yield, quality, everything should be good
產量啊 品質啊 什麼都要好
Now the COA starts
那現在農委會開始
have this plan
有這個計畫
They're the ones that are going to start pre-soybeans
他們就是要開始預大豆的品種
That is to say, the varieties suitable for growing in Taiwan
就是說適合在台灣生長的品種
that so they go from there
那所以他們從那裡
From the strict warehouse of the serious name
從那個嚴肅名的總嚴庫裡面
There are some of this encouraging
有一些這個鼓勵的
That strange wheat has
那奇怪怪小麥都有
so i want roommates here
所以我想室友在座
but not a lot of people here
但是沒有很大量的在座
so maybe that means
那所以也許就是說
roommate in need
室友有需要
because if you really want to
因為如果說真的是要
Don't root those fields
把那些農地不要修根
I think the most important thing is to
我想最重要就是要
produce other encouragement
生產別的鼓勵
Even the so-called production so-called feed name
甚至所謂生產所謂的飼料名
Because our greatest consumption
因為我們最大量的消耗
In fact, you raise pigs and chickens
其實是你養豬 養雞
these things
這些東西
So you have to help Taiwan's food security
所以你要幫助台灣糧食安全
Everyone eats a bowl of rice every day
每個人每天都吃一碗米
It's all bowls
都是一碗碗
Because it is a surprise demand
因為是surprise demand
if you eat more
你如果吃得多
That means the price of rice will rise
那就是米價就會高起來
So this is a
所以這個是一個
you change your eating habits
你改變你的飲食習慣
the second is
第二個就是
because you have less meat
因為你肉類少
Your bottom faces the bottom of this encouragement
你的底面對那個這個鼓勵的底
less inside
裡面就少了
The other one is the government's business
那另外一個就是政府的事
just to start planting
就是要開始種
Even rice can be used as fodder
甚至米都可以拿來當飼料
So now the Agricultural Committee forbids us to say this
所以現在有農委不准我們講這個話
because you talk about feed rice
因為你講飼料米
He wonders why the rice you produce is used as feed
他就覺得你生產的米怎麼拿來當飼料
He's afraid of you two getting together
他怕你兩個混在一起
So we have to think of a better one now
所以我們現在就要想一個好一點
That is, if you use it as feed rice
就是你如果當飼料米的話
You probably don't need that high quality
你大概就是品質不用那麼高
You can just go for a lot of that sort of thing
你可以就大量就是種類這一類的
So there are some scholars
那所以是有一些學者
Then we were doing it during the seminar
然後我們在討論會的時候有在做
Several agricultural cover factories of the Council of Agriculture are slowly working on it
農委會幾個農蓋廠有慢慢的在做
But maybe there needs to be a country
但是也許是需要有一個國家的
For example, another national project
譬如說再來一次國家性計畫
plan this down
把這個規劃下來
Then I feel like it's not like it used to be
然後我覺得不是像以往的就是
from the bottom one
由底下的那個
proposed by the researchers themselves
由研究人員自己來提出
but you want a top down
而是你要一個top down
That is to say, task marriage
就是說任務婚族
Which group of you do what kind of things
你哪一組人做哪一些方面的東西
do this
這樣子做
That is to timely benefit
那就是要及時廣益
what we need in the next ten years
我們未來十年需要什麼
Then mix this job down
然後把這個工作混下去
then i think
那我想
Taiwan can do it, absolutely no problem
台灣可以做的來 絕對沒問題
I will leave the last minute to Dean Li.
我把最後一分鐘讓給李院長 來
Because I just challenged you to say that your two things are contradictory
因為我剛才跟你挑戰說你的兩個事情是矛盾的
so i'm going to save you
所以我要替你解圍
Thank you Dean Li
謝謝李院長
It is very important that the government takes the lead in people's participation
那個政府帶頭人民參與 這個是非常重要的
because it didn't work
因為這一點沒做到
That's why I've been talking about the measurement points of Taiwan's farmers.
才把台灣農民的量點一直拿出來講
But you just talked about the food supply rate of 33%
但是你剛才談到糧食供應自己率33%
Near future
不久的將來
When the world's food supply is not enough for everyone to eat
全世界糧食的供應不夠大家吃的時候
Taiwan, whose food supply rate is low, is the first to be hurt
糧食供應自己率少的台灣是第一個受到傷害的
This is a problem that the government should take the lead in solving
這個是政府要帶頭解決的問題
So you were talking about problems like this farmhouse Hugh
所以剛才你談到的是像這個農舍的問題 休更的問題
Many of these issues are to be addressed by the government
這些很多問題都是政府帶頭要做的
We now say that the United States has a lot of pressure
我們現在說美國有很大的壓力
The markets of our agricultural products are all open
我們的農產品都市場要開放
But is our participation in this TPP good for farmers?
但是我們參加這個TPP對農民好嗎
He did a lot of good things for the government, but it will be miserable in the future
是為政府帶領做很多好事 將來會很慘的
These things are good government for us
這些事情是我們要好的政府
representative of the good people
好的人民的代表
this is a very important thing
這是一件很重要的
That's why I just said I heard you make a rescue
所以我剛才說我聽你解圍的就是
we didn't do that
我們這一點沒做到
Only then did I bring up the highlights of many farmers in Taiwan
才把台灣的很多農民的亮點提出來說
we are good
我們是不錯的
The first point is done
第一點做到了
we can have a good future
我們才能夠有好的將來
so
所以
don't listen to your rescue
不聽你解圍
Thank you Li Yanze
謝謝李彥澤
thank you
謝謝各位
Great speech thank you all
精采的演講 謝謝各位